<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Romane centurion becomming a good souldier of Iesus Christ In foure sermons, preached in the cathedrall church, and in Saint Thomas Church at Sarum. By Bartholomevv Parsons, B.D. and rector of Ludgershall, in the county of Wiltes.</title>
            <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19350.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124821</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898716</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2013:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Romane centurion becomming a good souldier of Iesus Christ In foure sermons, preached in the cathedrall church, and in Saint Thomas Church at Sarum. By Bartholomevv Parsons, B.D. and rector of Ludgershall, in the county of Wiltes.</title>
                  <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 87, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M.D. and are to be sold by Henry Hammond, booke-seller in Salsbury,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>STC reports variant with "sold" misspelled "sosd" in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1475-1640 reel 2013 lacks pages 73-80.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152101:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ROMANE CENTVRION BECOMMING A GOOD Souldier of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>IN FOVRE SERMONS, Preached in the Cathedrall Church, and in Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> Church at <hi>Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By BARTHOLOMEVV PARSONS, <hi>B.D.</hi> and Rector of <hi>Ludgerſhall,</hi> in the County of <hi>Wiltes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EPH. 6. VERSE</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13.</hi> Take unto you the whole armour of God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14.</hi> Stand therefore having your Loynes girt about with truth, and having on the breſt-plate of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>M. D.</hi> and are to be ſoſd by <hi>Henry Hammond,</hi> Booke-ſeller in <hi>Salsbury,</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152101:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152101:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:152101:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152101:4"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HONOVRED, Generous, and Religious, Mr IOHN POPHAM Eſquire, a true ſervant <hi>to God, his King and his</hi> COVNTREY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>NOBLE SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ertue which was to others an Autumne, late ripe fruite, budded to the Caeſars in their ſpring time, <hi>Caeſaribus virtus contigit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me diem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ovid.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Dame vertue did their portion frankly pay</l>
               <l>unto the Ceſars, long before their day.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And Honour the ſhadow following this great body of vertue, which to moſt is a winter-f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſcarce over ripening, is to you a Primroſe, ſpringing up in the Prime of the dayes, <hi>Gloria Pophamo contigit ante diem.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Honour which towards others keepes ſuch ſtate</l>
               <l>On Popham early did beginne to waite.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:152101:5"/>
You are as honourable in the hearts, affections and tongues of all that know you in theſe parts, as if all the titles and complements of Honour which in a ſtate are conferred upon eminent Perſons, had beene already heaped upon you. And although (as the Prince of Philoſophers long ſince pronounced) <hi>honoreſt in honorante magis quàm in honorato,</hi> honour be rather in him that honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth then in him that is honoured, yet this Honour in you will be as indeleble a Character, as that which accrueth by bloud, is accounted by the Men of Law. For as amongſt the old Romanes there was no way to the Temple of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour but through the Temple of Vertue, ſo you have gone the high way to this Honour, by thoſe vertues that are of a Magneticall vertue to draw to them the hearts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of men;<note place="margin">Si vis benè au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire, diſcito benè loqui, &amp; cum benè lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui didiceris, rectè etiam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere conator, Hoc enim modo bonam famam acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Epict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus.</note> your Humanity, Humility, and Hoſpitality If thou wilt have a good name, learne to ſpeake fairely and when thou haſt learned that, indevour to do well alſo; For hy this meanes thou ſhalt get a good report, ſaid <hi>Epictetus,</hi> or as <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Apophthegmes</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it more roundly, the way to a good fame is, <hi>Si dices optima, facies pulcherrima,</hi> by ſweete language and faire deeds. Your Humanity is ſuch, that even for that you are as <hi>Titus</hi> the Romane Emperour was called in his time <hi>deliciae humani generis,</hi> the darling of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, and that which <hi>Plutarke</hi> ſaid of <hi>Alcibiades,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biade</note> is appliable to you, he was ſo ſweete and pleaſant in his dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſing that even to them which did either fear c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>envy him,<note place="margin">Si quis cogitat conſtituere magnam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricam celſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis, is prins de fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to humilitatis cogitet.</note> his preſence and aſpect was pleaſant &amp; ioyfull And for Humility, you have ever bin ſo lowly in your owne eyes, that for it you have bin highly honoured in the eyes of other men. For, if any man thinke to erect the great fabricke of dignity, let him firſt thinke upon the foundation of humility. Dignity delighteth all men but
<pb facs="tcp:152101:5"/>humility is the ſtep to it.<note place="margin">Omnes dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat celſitudo, ſed humilitas gra-dus eſt. Quid tendis ordem ultra te? Cadere vis non aſcendere A gradu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe &amp; aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſti: <hi>Aug. de verb. Dom.</hi>
               </note> Why doſt thou lift thy foote be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond thy ſelfe? that's the way to fall downe, not to clime up, begin at the ſtep, and thou haſt already climed up. And for Hoſpitality you have ever bin ſo mind full to intertain neighbours and ſtrangers, that few great Houſes in our parts can contend or compare for free, frequent and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent intertainement with your Litle-coate<note n="(b)" place="margin">The name of his Manſion houſe.</note> that though you have not had the happineſſe with <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> to entertaine Angells in the ſhape of men,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.2.</note> yet it hath bin your happineſſe and goodneſſe too, frequently to entertaine the men that are the Angels of the Churches, and of late our reverend Dioceſan, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Angel of the Churches within his Dioceſe. And your Hoſpitality hath bin ſo ſeaſoned with Affability, that as <hi>bis dat, qui citò dat,</hi> he giveth doubly that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſpeedily, ſo <hi>bis dat, qui tam alacriter dat,</hi> he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth doubly, that entertaineth ſo cheerefully, it is the higheſt commendation of entertainment in the Poet, that <hi>ſuper omnia vultus acceſſere boni,</hi> above all there were added kinde countenances, and the counſaile of the wiſe man, <hi>In all thy gifts ſhew a cheerefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 35 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit it is not the Contemplation of theſe faire graces in you (<hi>quid enim ſunt bona noſtra, niſi dona dei?</hi> what are our good deeds, but Gods good graces in us?) that onely animateth me to preſent and Dedicate this piece of my labours to you. (For as <hi>Varus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar, Quiapud te non audent dicere, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant humanitatem tuam,</hi> they that dare not ſpeake in thy preſence, are ignorant of thine humanity) nor yet the relation of that long acquaintance that I have had with your ſelfe and your beſt friends, but alſo and much more the juſt conformity and correſpondence of the Perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated
<pb facs="tcp:152101:6"/>of in theſe Sermons with your ſelfe and your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, that ſo I may ſay with the Kingly Preacher, <hi>there is no new thing done under the Sun</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eccl. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>and that which hath bin is now</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eccl. 3.15</note> and againe that with the men of <hi>Berea,</hi> you are every way as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as noble in receiving Gods word with all diligence of minde and ſearching the Scriptures<note n="(b)" place="margin">Act. 17.11.</note> and other Heroicall and Chriſtian vertues as even <hi>Cornelius</hi> was. For, He for his civill ſtate, was a Centurion or Captaine of an hundred at <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> farre out of his owne Countrey of <hi>Italy,</hi> you have the honour in your own Countrey to be more then a Centurion a Deputy Lievetenant in this Country for Military Diſcipline and a Colonell of diverſe bands. He was a ſervant to the Roman <hi>Ceſar Tiberius</hi> (who by j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt computation then reigned, a wiſe and politike Prince, but withall crafty, cruell, perfidious, &amp; Laſcivious, you are Domeſticall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to our Soveraigne, who is <hi>alterius orhis Caeſar,</hi> the <hi>Ceſar</hi> of this other <hi>Britaine</hi> world (as Pope <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ban</hi> called <hi>Anſelme</hi> our Archbiſhop <hi>alterius or bis Papam</hi>) and who equalleth the beſt that were of that ranke, or his politicall and morall vertues of wiſedome temperance fortitude, clemency and moderate government, but farre exceedeth them in Religion Piety knowledge and ſervice of the true God, and aſſured hope of a Crowne that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.4.</note> undefiled, like the ſtone <hi>Amian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and unfading like the flower <hi>Amarantus</hi> Againe for Religion, He was a devout man, and one that feared God, you are therein a true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> without guile, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Profeſſour of the Orthodoxe faith and Religion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in this Church, becauſe it is in your conſcience Gods truth, and the right way of ſerving him, and not for any temporiſing reſpects of ſwimming with the ſtreame, nor for any feare or favour of men. He feared God with all his
<pb facs="tcp:152101:6"/>family, It hath ever bin your Fathers and your own reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and courſe with that brave leader of Iſrael <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to ſerve God with your whole houſhould<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ioſ. 24.15.</note> as thinking with the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius</hi> of his ſervants, that they could not keepe their faith inviolate towards him, that were perfidious to Almighty God<note n="(c)" place="margin">Euſeb de vita Conſtan. li. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> and to ſee that they be preſent at the ſet times of prayer, yea to compell them to come on the ſolemne dayes and times into Gods houſe that it may be full; He, if he had any wife in that houſhold to overſee their wayes, could not be happier in her, then you are in your loving and religious Conſort, who ſo ſympathizeth with you, that whither you goe, ſhe will go, where you lodge ſhe will lodge, your people are her people, and (which is beſt of all) your God is her God, and that nothing but death can part you &amp; her, as <hi>Ruth</hi> ſaith to <hi>Naomi</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ruth 1.16</note>. He gave much almes to the people round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, you not only like <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> entertaine yea invite and entreat into your houſe your neighbours, friends and ſtrangers, but alſo daily at your gates breake your bread, and open your almes basket to the poore of the Pariſhes round adjoyning, and refreſh their hungry bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elles. The Lord grant unto you that you may finde mercy of the Lord in that day. He with his pitty and charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men joyned piety towards God praying to God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and you do not onely ſerve God in righteouſneſſe and mercifulneſſe towards men, but alſo in holineſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him &amp; invocation of his name, you have a Church in your houſe, and an Oratory to ſerve God in, and you have your <hi>ſtata tempòra</hi> ſet times, which upon none oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion you omitte or intermitte. And I have this confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in you, that you have alſo your ſecret times of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into your Cloſet, and praying to your Father in ſecret<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> of communing with your owne heart upon your bedde
<pb facs="tcp:152101:7"/>and in private retiredneſſe.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> Now then <hi>macte virtute</hi> good lucke have thou with thine honour, ride on ſtill like a good plant in the houſe of the Lord, flouriſh ſtill in the Courts of our God, bring forth ſtill theſe fruits (amongſt your other fruits of Chriſtianity, both in your mature and old age<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 92.14</note> be ſtedfaſt &amp; unmooveable alwayes abounding in theſe workes of the Lord,<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> as you beleeve againſt all the enemies of grace, that the ſeed of grace ſowne in the good ground bringeth forth fruit with patience and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Luk. 8.15.</note> (the originall word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> importeth both) and that the Lord who is faithfull, will ſtabliſh his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in every good word and worke<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.3. and 2 17.</note> and confirme them unto the end<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.8</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that God who hath begun his good worke in you, wil finiſh it until the day of Chriſt, &amp; as he doth make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen and ſettle you in every good worke, ſo your reward ſhall be great in Heaven with him, he will abundantly recompence his owne gifts and good works in you, and crowne them with that crowne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which is laid up for all them that love the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of Ieſus Chriſt, in which bleſſed company that you may ever be found ſhall be the ſervent prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your devoted Servant in Chriſt Ieſuse <hi>BARTHOL. PARSONS.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Rectory at</hi> Ludgerſhall <hi>in the County of</hi> Wilts <date>
                     <hi>the 30.</hi> March <hi>1634.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152101:7"/>
            <head>A Romane Centurion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming a good Souldier of IESVS CHRIST.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION. I.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts cap. 10. verſ. 1, 2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p n="1">
                        <hi>1</hi> There was a certaine man in <hi>Ceſares,</hi> called <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius,</hi> a Centurion of the Band, called the Italian Band;</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2</hi> A devout man, and one that feared God with all his houſe, which gaue much almes to the people, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God alway.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the eight Chapter of this Booke, there appeares unto us certaine glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering ſparkles or flaſhes as it were of Gods purpoſe to call the <hi>Gentiles</hi> out of darkeneſſe to his marveilous light; both in the turning of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanes,</hi> (with whom before this time the <hi>Iewes</hi> might not meddle: for <hi>they had no dealings with the Samaritanes, Iohn</hi> 4.9. and into whoſe wayes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles at their firſt ſending out might not goe, <hi>into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny City of the Samaritanes enter yee not, Math.</hi> 10.5.) from the power of Satan to God, and alſo in giving the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Ieſus Chriſt unto the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> that came to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152101:8"/>to worſhippe. But in this the reſplendent beames of Gods good pleaſure in giving unto the Gentiles repentance unto life, ſhine cleerely unto us in an heavenly viſion both inſtructing and authoriſing <hi>Peter,</hi> that he being a <hi>Iew,</hi> might enter in to <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and the other <hi>Gentiles</hi> with him, and preach <hi>Chriſt Ieſus unto them.</hi> This whole Chapter then containing a narration of the full illuminating of <hi>Cornelius</hi> with the knowledge of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> alreadie come. In theſe two verſes propoſed is premiſed a deſcription of the perſon of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> either in his civill ſtate, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 1. <hi>There was a certaine man in</hi> Ceſarea <hi>called</hi> Cornelius, <hi>a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion of the Band called the Italian Band;</hi> or his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous both affections and actions, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>A devout man, and one that feared God with all his houſe, which gave much almes to the people, and prayed to God alway.</hi> In the former he is ſet out 1. By the place of his dwelling at <hi>Ceſarea.</hi> 2. By his profeſſion and calling, Hee was a Centurion of a Band, which Band is alſo particularly deſcribed, by the Countrey whence it came <hi>the Italian Band.</hi> In the latter his religious both affections and actions are declared generally or particularly: generally, <hi>He was a devout man,</hi> which is alſo amplified by an equivalent phraſe for fuller ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>and one that feared God:</hi> and alſo ſecondly by an adjoyned aſſociation, <hi>with all his houſe-hold.</hi> Particularly, by the fruits of his Religion; either in his charitie towards his brethren, or his pietie towards God: his charitie in giving <hi>almes,</hi> amplified 1. by the meaſure, <hi>much almes;</hi> 2. by the perſons, <hi>to the people.</hi> His pietie towards God in his prayers and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Hee prayed;</hi> which are alſo ſet out by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the perſon to whom, <hi>He prayed to God.</hi> 2. of the time, <hi>He did it alway.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To proſecute theſe particulars in their order, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin firſt with the firſt circumſtance of his civill ſtate, whereby he is ſet out unto us, the place of his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at <hi>Ceſarea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152101:8"/>
There were two famous Cities of this name amongſt the <hi>Iewes:</hi> one the elder which was called <hi>Turris Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonis,</hi> but being amplified by <hi>Herod</hi> the Great, and adorned with many workes worthy the ſight, was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him <hi>Ceſarea</hi> to winne the favour of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> as reporteth <hi>Ioſephus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de bello Iud: cap.</hi> 16 and <hi>lib.</hi> 15. <hi>Antiq. cap.</hi> 13. As alſo from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours daughter <hi>Iulia,</hi> this <hi>Herod</hi> built <hi>Iulias,</hi> on the farther ſide of <hi>Iordan, Hiero. in Matth.</hi> 16. And it was ſcituate on the coaſt of the <hi>Mediterranean Sea,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Dora</hi> and <hi>Ioppa,</hi> The other being later, was ſcituate in <hi>Iturea</hi> in <hi>Trachonitis,</hi> a Countrey of <hi>Galile</hi> or <hi>Phoenicia,</hi> at that part of Mount <hi>Libanus</hi> where the two Rivers <hi>Ior</hi> and <hi>Dan</hi> meete together and make the River <hi>Iordan, Hier. vbi ſuprà.</hi> It was anciently called <hi>Paneas,</hi> of a River of that name which ranne by it, and reckoned in the number of the famous Cities of <hi>Decapolis;</hi> but being afterward increaſed and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by <hi>Philip</hi> ſonne of <hi>Herod</hi> the Great, and <hi>Tetrarch</hi> of <hi>Galilee Luke</hi> 3. it was called by him <hi>Ceſarea</hi> in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> and for diſtinction ſake <hi>Ceſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea Philippi.</hi> Afterwards <hi>Agrippa</hi> to flatter <hi>Nero</hi> called it <hi>Neronias: Ioſeph lib.</hi> 20. <hi>antiq. cap.</hi> 8. Of theſe the former is here meant.</p>
               <p>Now this rocke is not ſo ſtonie but if we ſtrike it the waters will guſh out, from the verball denomination of this place we may haue a reall obſervation, to note the vaine pride, and proud vanitie of the ſonnes of men, the Princes of this world and their followers and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, in calling houſes and Cities after their owne names. And I ſpeake not this according to man,<note place="margin">In terminis terminan tibus.</note> it is the Holy Ghoſts cenſure of them in expreſſe termes, <hi>They call their lands after their owne names, Pſal.</hi> 40.11. And this pride is none of the new upſtart faſhions of yeſterday, it is as old as the ancienteſt Citie that was built: <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt builder of a Citie (for <hi>Seth</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> built none, but lived in Tents, to ſhew that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152101:9"/>they had none abiding City here) called the name of it after the name of his ſonne <hi>Enoch, Gen.</hi> 4.17. That one Citie <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ſometimes Heathen, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Chriſtian, now Turkiſh, hath changed its names as often as <hi>Laban</hi> did <hi>Iacobs</hi> wages, to flatter the great ones of the earth; at firſt it was called <hi>Lygo,</hi> then <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantium, Plin. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. afterwards, new <hi>Rome:</hi> In the time of <hi>Severus</hi> the Emperour and his ſonne <hi>Antonius, Antonia;</hi> afterwards of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, <hi>Conſtantinopolis,</hi> till it came to the <hi>Turkes</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, who tooke it <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1453. <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedone</hi> as <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> relateth of him, <hi>increaſing the City</hi> Crenidae <hi>with ſtore of Inhabitants,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>changed the name of it into</hi> Philippi, <hi>ſo calling it of himſelfe.</hi> And <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great his ſonne in divers places where he obtained victories, erected Cities calling them by his name <hi>Alexandria</hi> or <hi>Alexandropolis,</hi> the famouſeſt of all which was <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt.</hi> But I cannot waſte time in running into particular inſtances in this kinde, and they would make me keepe ſilence for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matter.</p>
               <p>If any one aske, to what end? The Holy Ghoſt that cenſures their fact,<note place="margin">Cui bono?</note> ſheweth their end in it. It was that they might be as an <hi>Abſoloms</hi> piller to keepe their names in remembrance, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Their inward thought is, that their houſes ſhall continue for ever, and their dwelling places to all generations, they call their lands after their owne names Pſal.</hi> 49.11. And as the Holy Ghoſts imputation layeth this upon them, ſo their owne profeſſion expreſſeth ſuch an intention, <hi>Let us</hi> (ſay the firſt builders of the towne of <hi>Babel</hi>) <hi>build us a Citie and a Towre, whoſe top may reach unto heaven, and let us make us a name, leaſt we be ſcattered abroad upon the face of the whole earth, Gen.</hi> 11.4. And ſuch a ſpirit will be found in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> a ſucceſſor of theirs in <hi>Bab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l,</hi> one that had made it great; <hi>Is not this great Babylon, that I haue built for the houſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152101:9"/>of the Kingdome, by the might of my power, &amp; for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of my majeſtie? Dan.</hi> 4.30. Howbeit this their way is but their folly <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49 13. In vaine doe they labour to eternize their names in this world which paſſeth away &amp; the figure therof 1 Cor. 7.31. <hi>that which now is, in the dayes to come, ſhalbe forgotten Eccl.</hi> 2.16. <hi>they muſt depart in darkeneſſe and their names be covered with darkeneſſe Eccl.</hi> 6.4. The builders of <hi>Babel</hi> are confounded in language and ſcattered upon the whole earth before their tower could be erected <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. <hi>and Babylon</hi> it ſelfe growing afterwards to be the glory of kingdomes and the beauty of the <hi>Chaldees</hi> excellency, muſt be ouerhrowne as when God ouerthrew <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> it ſhall neuer be inhabited, neither ſhall it be dwelt in from generation to generation <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 13.19.20. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> for his pride muſt be put from his Kingdome and made know that the Lord is able to abaſe them that walke in pride <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.28.37. And thoſe great houſes that are built that men may dwel alone in the earth, haue either this curſe upon them that they ſhall be deſolate and without inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.8.9. or elſe to be ſmitten till they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, <hi>I will ſmite the winter houſe with the ſummer houſe: and houſes of Iuory ſhall periſh: and of the great houſes there ſhall be an end, ſaith the Lord, Amos</hi> 3.15.</p>
               <p>But on the otherſide the generation of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren even in theſe denominations of places, haue not ſought their owne glory but Gods: <hi>they whether they eate or drinke or whatſoever they doe, doe all to the glory of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. have rather deſired to build to his name, then to get themſelves a name: When God looked upon <hi>Abraham</hi> and prouided him a Ramme, to Sacrifice in ſtead of his ſonne, he called the name of that place <hi>Iehova yreh, the Lord will ſee or provide, Gen.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Iacob</hi> called the place where the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto him in a dreame at his going into <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan-Aram
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152101:10"/>Bethel,</hi> the houſe of God <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.19. and where he wreſtled with him at his comming backe from thence <hi>Penuel,</hi> the face of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.30. And <hi>David</hi> the firſt thing that he thought upon after God had given him reſt from his enemies round about, was to build an houſe to Gods name 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he voweth that <hi>he would not come into the tabernacle of his houſe, nor goe up into his bed, that he would not give ſleepe to his eyes: or ſlumber to his eye-lids, untill he had found out a place for the Lord: an habitation for the mighty God of Iacob. Pſal.</hi> 1.32.2.3.4.5. Oh how farre have ourſacrilegious times degenerated from the ancient and primitiue zeale of thoſe worthies! For now we are ſo farre from erecting conſecrating and conferring any thing to Gods name and worſhip, that we can dwell in <hi>Seiled houſes and let Gods houſe lie waſte Hag.</hi> 4. yea ſiele our houſes with the waſte of Gods houſe, with <hi>Tobiah,</hi> chamber our ſelues in the courts of the houſe of God, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.7. with <hi>Belſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> feaſt and ryot with the ſpoyles of the Lords temple <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.3. and not onely with <hi>Ananias and Sapphira</hi> pull backe that which we or our anceſtors have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to God <hi>Act.</hi> 5. but alſo devoure that which we never dedicated, reape that away from Gods Goſpell, that we never ſowed to Gods glory. The time and the tune is changed and it is not now, <hi>Let us give houſes to God to poſſeſſe, but under</hi> the profeſſion of the Goſpell, we ſpeake the language of <hi>Paganiſme. Let us take to our ſelues the houſes of God in poſſeſſion. Pſal.</hi> 83.12. But lament this we may, amend it we cannot, only this we are ſure of, that whoſoever theſe devourers are, they ſhall beare their iniquity.</p>
               <p>So I paſſe from the place of his dwelling to the ſecond circumſtance in his civill ſtate, his profeſſion &amp; calling which is a <hi>Centurion of a band.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> legion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of 6100. footemen, of 730. horſe-men was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152101:10"/>into 10. ſeverall cohortes or troupes,<note place="margin">Era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Centuriones qui ſingulas centurius cure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, qui n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c centenarij appel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter vegetius lib. <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> and thoſe of an unequall number as we may ſee in <hi>Vegetius lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 8. The cohortes againe were ſubdivided into Centuries, handreds over which Captaines were ſet called Centurions, <hi>they were Centurions who had the charge of euery band of an hundred, who are now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alled Centenaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for his office and profeſſion, ſome arts and profeſſions are vnlawfull in their very conſtitution and cannot ſtand with the profeſſion of godlineſſe; ſuch were thoſe curious arts of Magicke and ſorcery uſed by many at Epheſus, who when they were brought to the faith, brought their bookes and burned them in deteſtation of their arts <hi>Act.</hi> 19.18.19; ſuch was that craft of <hi>Demetrius</hi> and the other Smithes that gate their living by making ſiluer <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <hi>Diana,</hi> ſhrines or coynes whereon the Temple and Image of <hi>Diana</hi> was ſtamped <hi>Act.</hi> 19. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. And ſuch are too many vocations in ours and every Common-wealth, being avocations from all piety and goodneſſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations to and ſomentations of all impiety, riot and prophaneneſſe. Others againe have a lawfull and neceſſary uſe, but are for the moſt part abuſed by the corruption, of thoſe that exerciſe them. Such was the office of the Publicanes, who being Farmours of the <hi>Roman</hi> Tributes exacted more then their due, as we may ſee both by <hi>Zacheus</hi> confeſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>If I have taken any thing from any man by falſe accuſations Luke.</hi> 19.8. and by <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> limitation given them when they came to the Baptiſme, <hi>take no more then that which is appointed you Luk.</hi> 3. Such was the calling of ſouldiers lawfull in it ſelfe, but ſeldome lawfully uſed: For if it were not lawfull, God would neither have comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it ſo oft in Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.19. Nor the men of God <hi>Moſes, Ioſhua David</hi> and the reſt have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken it, nor <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> have preſcribed rules to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152101:11"/>convert ſouldiers how to behave themſelves in their office ſaying unto them <hi>doe violence to no man, neither accuſe any falſely, and be content with your wages, Luke</hi> 3.14. but vtterly have forbidden:<note place="margin">Militare noneſt delictum, ſed propter pradam mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare peccatum eſt Aug. de verbo Dom: difficulter continentur ſuo termino, facilè autemalieno. Ariſt. lib. <hi>2</hi> de art text. <hi>9.</hi> Nulla fides pietaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> viris qui caſtra ſequun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Luc. lib. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the calling to warre is no fault, but to warre for the prey, is a fault.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if we looke to the lawfull uſing of it, like that definition of <hi>humidum,</hi> they are hardly conteined in their owne bounds, but eaſily in anothers bounds. They fight not for the right but to get the booty, and under colour of warring, they make a trade of robbing <hi>There is no faith, or piety to be found in Martiall men,</hi> ſaith the Poet. The corruption then of his office lay like a Lyon in the way to keepe him from Chriſt. And beſides natures backwardnes naturall to all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> he had the earthly <hi>Mammon</hi> a Remora to hinder him from ſerving his heavenly Maſter, and the vaine idoles of the Romanes (for his name <hi>Cornelius</hi> argueth him to be a Roman, and S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. well obſerue that no Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turions were made of the Iewiſh people) to turne him away from the living God.</p>
               <p>But (which is our inſtruction in this particular) the winde of Gods grace bloweth where it luſteth and none can let it, and the net of his Goſpell catcheth fiſhes of all ſorts, He bringeth into his ſheepefold <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and the men of warre that came to <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> out of ſouldiers and ſwaggerers: a <hi>Manaſſes</hi> out of Idolaters, a <hi>Rahab,</hi> a <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> out of harlots; the wiſemen that came to Chriſt <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. and thoſe that uſed curious arts at Epheſus <hi>Act.</hi> 19.19. out of Conjurers and Sorcerers: a <hi>Mathew</hi> out of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanes: a <hi>Zacheus</hi> out of oppreſſours: the Prodigall ſonne out of riotours: Scribes and Phariſees out of the generation of vipers, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. a <hi>Paul</hi> out of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors: a <hi>Peter</hi> out of renegates and forſwearers: many of the Iewes and Prieſts out of the crucifiers of Chriſt <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.7. the good theefe on the Croſſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152101:11"/>out of robbers: Goaler out of unmercifull perſons, <hi>Act.</hi> 16. Saints at <hi>Corinth,</hi> out of fornicators, idolaters, adulterers, <hi>effeminate, abuſers of themſelues with man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, theeues, covetous, drunkards, revilers, extoritio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9.10. and in a word, <hi>out of ſtones</hi> (men as deſtitute of ſpirituall life, as the ſtones are of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall) <hi>hee can raiſe up children to Abraham, Math.</hi> 3.9. to walke in the ſteppes of the faith of <hi>Abraham. Rom.</hi> 4.12.</p>
               <p>Here then is ſpirituall wiſedome both for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and inſtruction: Conſolation, if the number of our ſinnes terrifie us, being more in number then the haires of our head; if the greatneſſe of them daunt us, being as bigge as the mightie mountaines, and a burthen to heavie for us to beare; if an accuſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience would be readie to cry out with <hi>Cain, mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie is greater then that it may bee forgiven, Gen.</hi> 4.13. If Satan the accuſer of our brethren would ſet upon us to accuſe us, let us comfort our ſelues in our God that ſaveth ſinners of all ſorts, let us flie unto him from whence commeth our ſalvation, and our faces ſhall not be aſhamed:<note place="margin">Omninò propter man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinom quae eſt in te domime Ieſu, curri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus poſt te &amp;c. <hi>Bern. Serm.</hi> 22 <hi>in Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> let us repent and bee converted and all our iniquities ſhall be blotted out, <hi>Altogether for the weekeneſſe that is in thee O Lord Ieſu</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>wee runne after thee,</hi> hearing that thou deſpiſedſt not the poore ſinner, abhorredſt not the confeſſing theefe, nor the mourning ſinfull woman, nor the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> when ſhee requeſted thee, nor the woman ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in adulterie, nor the Publican praying unto thee, nor the Diſciple that denyed thee, nor yet him that perſecuted thy Diſciples, <hi>in the odor of theſe we runne after thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the inſtruction is both generall and particular: Generall, to all of us that wee deſpaire of no man, though he ſeeme to us to be never ſo deepe in the ſnare of Satan, much leſſe cenſure him to bee a reprobate and caſt out of the ſight of God, though in our ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152101:12"/>he be in the gall of bitterneſſe and bond of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, yea a tree without fruit, twice dead and pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked up by the rootes: for as the Apoſtle ſaid of the naturall branches broken off, that <hi>God was able to graffe them in againe, Rom.</hi> 11.23. ſo he is able to ſeeke and ſaue that which was loſt, to make the ſavageſt wolfe dwell with the lambe, yea to turne him into a lambe; and to bring into his familie the prodigalleſt child that is gone fartheſt from home. Vpon this ground the Apoſtle would haue us that are of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith to ſhew meekeneſſe to all men, becauſe we our ſelues ſometimes before wee taſted of grace, <hi>were fooliſh, diſebedient, deceived, ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures, living in malice and envie, hatefull, and hating others, Tit.</hi> 3.2.3. Even <hi>Iudas</hi> himſelfe was more the childe of hell by deſpairing of the mercy of God, then by delivering the ſonne of God into the hands of ſinfull men, by his impenitencie, then by his trecherie; by refuſing the grace of Chriſt, then by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the perſon of Chriſt. The Apoſtles indeede had in greater meaſure <hi>the gift of diſcerning of ſpirits,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. then now men have, and could cenſure men to be the children of the Devill, as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Act.</hi> 13.10. but for our part, howſoever we may judge the wayes and actions of wicked men to bee ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and damnable, yet wee may not pronounce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their perſons that they are reprobates, <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant? to his Master be ſtandeth or falleth, Rom.</hi> 14.4.</p>
               <p>The particular inſtruction is to Martiall men, to learne to joyne pietie to their profeſſion, the uſing of the ſword of the Spirit with the materiall ſword, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come good Souldiers of Ieſus Chriſt, aſwell as of their earthly Maſters: and to fight his battels, aſwell as their earthly Maſters quarrels. Wee ſee here that a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall profeſſion and a godly diſpoſition may meete to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as <hi>Hieroms</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cornelius, His Souldiers coat
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152101:12"/>and belt, and company of attendants hurt not this Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nil nocuit militanti paludamentum &amp; bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus &amp; apparitorum cetervae, quia ſub habi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> alterius alteri militabas Epiſt. ad Salvinam de viduitate ſervanda.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe under the habit of one hee was a Souldier to another.</hi> The military men of our age are glad to heare their calling juſtified by <hi>Cornelius</hi> his office, but care not to have their lives reformed after his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, wee may ſee and rejoyce that a <hi>Roman</hi> Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er here was ſo religious, but wee may ſee and ſorrow that our Chriſtian Souldiers every where are ſo vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>Hee was devout and feared God, with all his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> they thinke pietie no part of their profeſſion, yea, that is is want of ſpirit and courage in them not to bee at defiance with God and all godlineſſe, and not onely with <hi>Eſau</hi> to haue their hands againſt all men, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> to fight againſt God and to raile upon him,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18. and to thunder out their oathes and execrable blaſphemies. He opened his hands in the workes of mercie to the needie with him, their feete are as ſwift to ſhedde bloud as ever <hi>Herods</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who killed the infants of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> at his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Math.</hi> 2. He relieved the poore with his plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull almes, they pill them with their rapines, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abſtaine from things hallowed nor prophane: He was diligent and daily prayer; their mouthes are full of curſing and bitterneſſe, Chriſt is not in their hearts nor mouthes but to ſweare by his croſſe, paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, heart, bloud, wounds, and what not? Hee fell downe at <hi>Peters</hi> feete to giue him honour; their ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverent profaneneſſe is ſuch, that they are as readie to offer as great indignitie to Chriſts Miniſters and Meſſengers as <hi>Herod</hi> and his men of warre, as <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> and his Souldiers did to Chriſt in his perſon, <hi>Math.</hi> 27.27, 28, 29, 30, 31. In a word, he dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe to the workes of charitie and pietie; they like the Souldiers of the <hi>Amalekites</hi> giue themſelues to nothing but to eating, drinking, dancing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.16. He then of this calling, that having ſo little light walked ſo worthily as a childe of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152101:13"/>light, ſhall one day riſe in judgemen: againſt them of his profeſſion that having ſo great light ſhining to them, doe ſo wickedly as children of darkeneſſe.</p>
               <p>Now this band over which he was ſet, is particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed by the countrey whence it came, the name which it bare, the <hi>Italian</hi> band. For the <hi>Romanes</hi> ſometimes muſtered Souldiers out of the Provinces ſubject unto them, ſometimes out of <hi>Italie</hi> it ſelfe and the territories thereof. But what maketh the <hi>Italian</hi> hand at <hi>Ceſarea</hi> here? what doe the Heathen amongſt Gods Inheritance? the <hi>Italian</hi> troupe amongſt the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> people? Aſſuredly Beloved, the people of the <hi>Iewes</hi> were a precious people unto God aboue all the people of the earth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6. his choſen portion and his peculiar treaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.4. unto whom he would <hi>ſuffer none to doe wrong, but reproved even Kings for their ſakes: ſaying, touch not mine annointed, and doe my Prophets no harme, Pſal.</hi> 105.14.15. Yea the Lord hath choſen <hi>Sion</hi> and loved to dwell in it ſaying, <hi>This is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell for I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it, Pſal.</hi> 132.13.14. <hi>He ſhewed his word unto Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, his ſtatutes and his judgements unto Iſrael, he hath not dealt ſo with any Nation, Pſal.</hi> 147.19.20. To them pertained the adoption, and the glory, and the Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and the promiſes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. <hi>In</hi> Iudah <hi>is God knowne, his name is great in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>in</hi> Salem <hi>alſo is his Tabernacle, and his dwelling place in</hi> Sion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.1.2. But when this faithfull City became an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, when her ſilver was turned into droſſe. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.21 22. when they did evill in the ſight of the Lord, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke the Covenant of the Lord their God, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after ſtrange Gods and ſerved them, <hi>his anger was hot againſt them, and he delivered them into the hands of ſpoylere that ſpoyled them, and he ſold them into the hands of their enemies round about, ſo that they could not any longer ſtand before their enemies, Iudg.</hi> 2.12,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152101:13"/>13, 14. when they were diſobedient and rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and caſt his Law behinde their backes, and ſlew his Prophets which teſtified againſt them to turne them to him, and wrought great provocations, he delivered them into the hands of their enemies who vexed them in the time of their trouble; <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.26, 27. So that, <hi>they that hated them were Lords over them, Pſal.</hi> 106.41. And ſometimes he ſold them into the hands of their enemies that were round about them, who vexed them and ſpoyled them, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee brought upon them a Nation from farre whoſe language they did not know, nor underſtand what they ſaid, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.15. As now at this time <hi>Shiloh</hi> being come, <hi>the Scepter was departed from</hi> Iudah, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.10. and they ſerved the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rerum domini:</note> who at this time were as the Poet ſpeaketh <hi>Maisters of the world,</hi> and had by <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great overcome <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>India,</hi> and made them ſubject to their Empire. And the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> placed their troups in theſe parts, partly to keepe under the Iewiſh nation apt to rebellion and to ſhake off the yoake (for they much ſcorned ſubjection <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.33.) partly to with-ſtand the hoſtility of the <hi>Parthians,</hi> who were deadly enemies to them, made outroades into their Empire, and were famous for the killing of <hi>Craſſus,</hi> ſlaughtering of the <hi>Roman</hi> legions and taking of their Eagles the enſignes of the Empire.</p>
               <p>Now Beloved, to come home with this to our ſelves, hath God done <hi>this in the greene tree what ſhall be done in the drie? Luk.</hi> 23.31. hath he not ſpared the naturall branches that ſinned? let us that are but the wild olive tree grafted in amongſt them and with them, partakers of the roote and fatneſſe of the olive-tree, take heed leaſt he ſpare not us for our rebellions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.21. Aſſuredly the Apoſtle giveth us a rule that muſt hold in all the judgements that befell them, <hi>theſe things happened to them for enſamples,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and they are written for our admonition</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. Their corrections then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152101:14"/>muſt be our inſtructions. For are not wee as <hi>Iſay</hi> calleth them a <hi>ſinfull nation, a people laden with iniquity, a ſeed of evill doers, children that are corrupters: that have forſaken the Lord, that have provoked the holy one of Iſrael to anger and gene away backeward: our whole head is ſicke and our whole heart faint: from the ſole of the feet, even unto the head there is no ſoundneſſe: but wounds and bruiſes and putrifying ſores Iſay</hi> 1.4.5.6. <hi>are not we a nation not worthy to be beloved, as Zephaniah</hi> calleth them, <hi>a nation not deſired</hi> Zeph. 2.1. <hi>have not we made our faces harder then a recke and refuſed to turne unto God? Ier.</hi> 5.3. may not the Lord ſend an inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into our ſtreets and not finde a righteous man, neither amongſt poore nor great? <hi>Ier.</hi> 5. may not the Lord have a controverſie againſt the inhabitants of the land, becauſe <hi>there is no truth, nor mercy, nor know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God in the land: by ſwearing and lying, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and ſtealing, and committing adulterie, we breake out and bloud toucheth bloud. Hoſ.</hi> 4.1.2. Are not the ſinnes of <hi>Sodome</hi> pride, fulnes of bread, abundance of idlenes, haughtineſſe, and abomination before God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.49. in ſuch exceſſe amongſt us, as they were amongſt them? that we are more corrupt in our wayes ſo that <hi>Sodome</hi> if it now ſtood might be juſtifyed in compariſon of us <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. See we not the falling away of many of our people to Popery? the luke-warmner and neutrality of others, as tempering themſelves to every time? the licentiouſnes and diſſolutenes of all orders and degrees, ouergrowne with pride, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flown with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe, ſometimes the ſhame of beggers, now the glory of Gallans? How many blazing ſtarres of pride may we meete in every place? How many ſonnes and daughters of our Sion dreſſed up in the toyes and tyres that <hi>Iſay</hi> complaineth of <hi>Iſay</hi> 3. in the ſtrange apparell to which <hi>Zephany</hi> threateneth a puniſhment <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>What a generation is there riſen up in our dayes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152101:14"/>more then ever in the daies of our forefathers, of them that are mighty to drinke wine, and men of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong drinke. <hi>Iſa</hi> 5.22. that cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to fill themſelves with wine and ſtrong drinke, but muſt needes draw others to hell with them, give them drinke to make them drunken alſo <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.15. of whom we may much better reaſon, ſee we not how much they drinke and devoure daily? are they not like the Angell of the bottomleſſe pit <hi>Apollions,</hi> deſtroyers <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. then <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> did concerning the idol <hi>Bel</hi> unto <hi>Daniel,</hi> thinkeſt thou not that <hi>Bel</hi> is a living God? ſeeſt thou not how much he eateth and drinketh every day? Hiſtory of <hi>Bel verſe</hi> 6. How inordinatly and idlely doe men amongſt us walke from the higheſt to the loweſt, from the Clergy to the Laity, not doing the workes of that calling wherein God hath ſet them, but either doing that which belongeth not to them or doing naughtily, or nothing? How juſtly might it be ſaid to us which <hi>Pharaoh</hi> unjuſtly to the Iſraclites, ye are idle?<note place="margin">Aliud agentes, aut male agentes, aut nihil agentes.</note> What defrauding and oppreſſing is there of one another in bargaining, in buying and ſelling? what ſlightneſſe in making of ware? what ſlights of falſe proteſtations, falſe oathes, falſe every thing in putting them off? men thinking that every thing which may be carried without danger of the Law, may be carried and done without danger of conſcience? What generall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe is there in mens hearts, tongues, actions, meetings, feaſtings without feare, who have (as <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaith) <hi>the Harpe and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iole, the Tabret and pipe, and wine in their feaſts: but they regard not the worke of the Lord, neither conſider the operation of his hands, Iſa.</hi> 5.12. nay make a ſcorne of his workes, words, meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers and all; and ſolace themſelves with ſcurrilous ſongs, not onely againſt the prince and ſtate, but even againſt Gods religion, and them that bring it, and them that beleeve it, no order is ſpared, the iuſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152101:15"/>man is laughed to ſcorne <hi>Iob</hi> 12.4.<note place="margin">Cum privilegio quod libet, licet.</note> Is not fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and uncleaneſſe which ſhould not be named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians practiſed by many as it were with a priviledge, who in this point thinke that which liketh them is Lawfull, &amp; deceive themſelves with vain words as though no wrath ſhould come upon them for this? What a cuſtome of that ſinne of ſwearing (that hath neither pleaſure nor profit in it the uſuall loadſtones of ſinne) hath that unruly member of moſt mens tongues gotten, ſo that all ſenſe of ſinning is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from us heerein? And how doth that <hi>intoxicating</hi> weed which God (who maketh every thing to good ends) made no doubt for ſome uſe and purpoſe, groane under the burthen of vanity, being made the incentive of drunkeneſſe, the tye of good fellowſhip, the common courteſie of the kingdome? I ſhould even looſe my ſelfe, if I ſhould particularly goe about to number up our numberleſſe iniquities. How then ſhould not God viſit us, and be avenged on ſuch a nation as wee are <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.29? this rod hath a long time beene ſhaken againſt us in ſundry places, yet all but gentle corrections, of parching heate, pinching cold, extreame drouth, exceſſive raine, dearth, famine, peſtilence, decay of the ſtate of the whole land; yet in all theſe we are fallen into his hands whoſe mercies are great, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.14. and not into the hands of open enemies or falſe friends whoſe mercies would be cruell, whoſe little finger would be heavier then Gods loynes 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.10.</p>
               <p>But if we ſtill walke contrary to God, what can we looke for, but that after all other his arrowes of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment drawne out of his quiver, he ſhould pull out this alſo, to call for a ſword upon us, make us fly before our enemies, nay to make them Lords over us? Though we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hinke with <hi>Eaom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> that we are high and ſecure, yet the Lord can pull us downe to the ground <hi>Obad.</hi> 3. Though we thinke with <hi>Tyrus</hi> that wee are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152101:15"/>ſtrong in the ſea, that we ſit as God in the midſt of the ſea, yet the Lord can make us deſolat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as the Cities that are not inhabited <hi>Ezek.</hi> 26.19. As God ſaid to old Iſraell doing all abominations, <hi>goe ye now int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my place which was in Shiloh; where I ſet my name at firſt, and ſee what I did to it, for the wickedneſſe of my people Iſrael Ier.</hi> 7.12. So may I to thoſe who walke fully in their wayes, goe ye to the primitive flouriſhing Churches of the Eaſt, ſee what God hath done to them for the wickedneſſe of the people, how there <hi>Mahomet</hi> hath ſet his foote where Chriſt onc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had his throne; nay we may come neerer home, and ſee with our eyes and lament in our hearts and voices that which God hath done to ſome of neighbour Churches in <hi>Germany;</hi> who held faſt his name, and did not deny his faith, no doubt amongſt other ends that he had to viſit them for denying him in their workes, for loving the works of darkenes and drunkenneſſe (the weede that moſt had over-runne their field) in ſuch a cleare light of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Tune tua res agiter paries cum proximus ardet.</note> when our neighbours houſe is on fire our owne is in danger. Feare and jelouſly is on every ſide <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levies</hi> policies and practiſes that may catch us in a ſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re under colour of friend ſhippe are not unknowne When we looke up to God and his Goſpell profeſſed amongſt us, there is hope that hee will give glory, <hi>not unto us, not unto us, but unto his name, leaſt the heathen ſay where is now their God, Pſal.</hi> 115.1.2. Leaſt his great name ſhould be blaſphemed amongſt the adverſaries of his truth. But when we caſt our eyes upon the lives of moſt of us that profeſſe the Goſpell and glory to be called Chriſtians, who are yet become abominable and reprobate unto every good worke; What can we thinke but that it is juſt with God to bring a ſtrong nation upon us, not onely to take way our place and nation, but alſo our Goſpell and candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152101:16"/>that hee may give his Goſpell to a people that will bring forth better fruit?</p>
               <p>Let us then (as <hi>Zephany</hi> counſelleth the Iewes) gather our ſelves together by true repentance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect and reunite our thoughts and wits formerly diſperſed, that we may conſider of our wayes before the decree come forth, before the day paſſe as the chaffe, before the fierce anger of the Lord come upon us, before the day of the Lords anger come upon us: let us ſeeke the Lord, which hath wrought his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, let us ſeeke righteouſneſſe and meekeneſſe: it may be we ſhall be hid in the day of the Lords anger <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.1.2.3 and as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi> let this be acceptable counſell to us, <hi>to breake off our ſinnes by righteouſneſſe, and our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities by ſhewing mercie to the poore, Dan.</hi> 4.27. that ſo the Lord may not onely let us dwell in our good land, and ſit every man in peace under his owne vine and fig-tree, eating the labours of his hand, but alſo enioy ſtill the abundance of the bleſſing of the Goſpell of Chriſt: What though the major part of men amongſt us lie in wickedneſſe? yet let us that now ſtand before the Lord this day reſolue with <hi>Ioſhua</hi> that <hi>wee and our houſehold will ſerve the Lord, Ioſhua</hi> 24.15. and depart from iniquity, which every one that calleth upon him muſt doe. We know that many times the righteous deliver the land accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of <hi>Philo Iudaeus, the wiſe man is the fooles redemption.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sapiens eſt flulti redemtio.</note> God would not have deſtroyed <hi>Sodome</hi> if ten righteous men had beene in it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. hee could doe nothing againſt it till <hi>Lot</hi> was gone out of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. he promiſed to pardon <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> if there could be found but one man that executed judgement &amp; ſought the truth <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.1. and he gave S. <hi>Paul</hi> the lives of all them that ſailed with him in the ſhippe in his dangerous voiage <hi>Act.</hi> 27. <hi>Scornefull men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>bring a citie into aſuare,</hi> but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152101:16"/>
                  <hi>wiſe men turne away wrath. Pro.</hi> 29.8. Howbeit if Gods anger were ſo kindled againſt this land and people, that he ſhould bid his ſervants as hee bad <hi>Ieremy,</hi> pray not for this people, neither lift up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> nor prayer for them, neither make interceſſion to me, for I will not heare you, mine anger and my fury ſhall be powred out upon man and upon beaſt, and upon the trees of the field, and upon the fruite of the gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, and it ſhall burne and ſhall not be quenched, <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.6. &amp; 20. that he ſhould proteſt as he doth to him, that, though <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> ſtood before him, yet his mind could not be toward the people <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.1. yet in ſuch a time and caſe, <hi>Noah Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Iob,</hi> every righteous man amongſt us, ſhould deliuer his owne ſoule by his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14. God will ſpare them that feare him as a man ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſerveth him when the day commeth that ſhall burne as an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ven, and all the proud, yea and all that doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loodly ſhall be ſtubble, and the day that ſhall burne them up, that it ſhall leave them neither roote nor branch, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1, to thoſe that feare the Lord we will hearken, and a booke of remembrance ſhall be written before him, for them that feare him and thinks upon his name, and they ſhall be mine ſaith the Lord, in that day when I make up my Iewells, and I will ſpare them as a man ſpareth his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſonne that ſerveth him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. If he would deliver them in ſixe troubles, yea in ſeven there ſhould no evill, touch them: in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he would redeeme them from death: and at w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re from the power of the ſword: they ſhould bee hid from the ſcourge of the tongue: neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ld they be afraid of deſtruction when it cometh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſtruction and famine they ſhould laugh: neither ſhould they bee, afraid of the beaſts of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152101:17"/>earth: for they ſhould bee in league with the ſtones of the field: and the beaſts of the field ſhould be at peace with them. And they ſhould know that their Tabernacle ſhall bee in peace, and they viſit their Tabernacle and ſhould not ſinne. They ſhould know that their ſeede ſhould be great and their off-ſpring as the graſſe of the earth. They ſhould come to their graves in a full age, like as a ſhocke of corne commeth in, in his ſeaſon <hi>Iob</hi> 5.19.20.21.22.23.24.25.26. Or elſe if hee ſhould ſuffer his owne ſervants to be inwrapped in the common calamities that hee bringeth upon a ſinfull nation and to drinke of the ſame Cup in outward ſhew with them, yet hee doth but therby chaſten them in this world, that they may not be condemned in the world to come, and he knoweth how to ſweeten all theſe corrections ſo to them, that they ſhall worke together for their good, that they ſhall not ſeparate them from the love of him, but that in all thoſe things they ſhall bee more then conquerours through him that hath loved them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. The ſame outward kinde of death it ſelfe with ſinfull men in a common ſcourge (as no doubt many of the 70000. that died in the plague for <hi>Davids</hi> numbring the people were the deare children of God) cannot ſeparate them that love God, from the love of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus; but is ſo ſanctified to them in Chriſts death upon the Croſſe, that it puts an end to their miſeries he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, and a beginning to their happineſſe that never ſhall have end, that it maketh them reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and is a paſſage and portall into Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſt.</p>
               <p>I doe but yet <hi>haerere in cortic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> I am but in the rind of this text <hi>Cornelius</hi> civill ſtate, and with <hi>Abraham</hi> ſit in the doore of this tent: but I ſee I ſhould
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152101:17"/>treſpaſſe againſt the time and your patience, to enter farther into it to make proviſion for you. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore with prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152101:18"/>
               <head>THE SECOND SECTION</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts 10. verſ. 2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>A devout man, and one that feared God with all his houſe, which gave much almes to the people, and prayed to God alway.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Cathedrall Church in <hi>Sarum.</hi> S. <hi>Thomas</hi> Church there.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the place where I firſt tooke in hand this text be changed, yet the Auditory being not changed, I will proceed in the handling of it according to the meaſure of the grace given unto me. When I firſt entred upon the firſt verſe heere, it ſeemed unto me like that place whereof the Children of the Prophets complained to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> that, <hi>the water was nought and the ground barren,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.19. But as the Prophet by caſting ſalt in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters there (the Lord working mightily by ſo weake a meanes) healed both the deadly taſte of the waters and barrenneſſe of the ground, verſes 21.22. So by the ſalt of Gods working (that his power might be perfected in his ſervants infirmitie 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.) it was ſo ſeaſoned and ſanctified to you that it yeelded both
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152101:18"/>the bread that periſheth not, and wholeſome and heavenly waters of life for the ſatisfying of them that hungred and thirſted after righteouſneſſe. I made a generall diviſion of the text into his civill ſtate, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. and his religious both affections and actions, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. of the former I have ſpoken formerly and largely;<note place="margin">Si tantivittum, quanti margarit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. <hi>Tertull.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and if glaſſe be worth ſo much, how much is pearle worth:</hi> If the particulars of his civill ſtate by comparing ſpirituall things with ſpirituall, did ſo plentifully af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us ſpirituall inſtructions: much more will the particulars of his religious both affections and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations by opening and interpreting of them be profitable for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. And although it were profitable for you that I ſhould ſpeake of the ſame thing in a ſummary repetition of that which I then delivered, yet hoping that at that time you not onely heard it, but alſo hid it within your hearts, I will paſſe and proceed to his religious affections and actions <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>I begin with the firſt ingenerall, <hi>A devout man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> In our common manner of ſpeaking devotion is oft reſtrained to the act and exerciſe of prayer, but here it muſt not be ſo limited. As a man that is religious, <hi>that doth live godly in Chriſt Ieſus</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Soberly and Righteouſly in this preſent world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tit,</hi> 2.12. Such an one as old <hi>Simeon,</hi> whom the Holy Ghoſt calleth juſt and devout <hi>Luke</hi> 2.25. and ſuch as the Proſelites that followed <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> who are called religious <hi>Act</hi> 13.43. as on the contrary is ungodly irreligious man, an ungodly and prophaneman, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. ungodly and ſinner, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18. Hee is here commended then for that affection and vertue which is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or worſhip of God, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.27. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7.8. and <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. and moſt properly and fully,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Aug. Epiſt. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and is defined to be a vertue infuſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152101:19"/>into our ſoules from God by his ſpirit whereby being made religious and godly wee both acknowledge and worſhip God aright,<note place="margin">Pietas propriè del cultus intelligi ſolet quam Graeci <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Vocant. <hi>Aug. de civit. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 1. Eſt verax dei cultus non falſorum to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deorum, quot daemonio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum lib. 4. cap. 23. ibidem. Religio eſt quae ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oris cujuſdam naturae, quam divinam vocant, curam ceremoniam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> affert. Quae eſt pietas niſi cultus dei? quis verò Deum colit, niſi qui ej voluntariè ſubjectus eſt, &amp; ſicut oculi Servo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in manibus domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum ſuorum, ſic oculi cord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us ad dominum Deum ſuum? <hi>Bern. in Natal. Dom Serm</hi> 4. Virtus vna, ſpecialis, moralium virtutum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliſſima, quae ſecundùm proprios actus deum tantummodò reſpicit, licè<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſecundùm actus aliarum virtutum ab ipſa imperato <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etiam proximum complecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. 22. <hi>qu.</hi> 81. Prompta &amp; parata vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas exequendiea quae ad divinum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tihent cultum. ibidem qu. 82. Religioeſt ſtatus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ad perfectionem Chriſtianam per pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertatis, continentiae &amp; obedientiae vota tendentium. controv: <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 5. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> according to his will revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his word. For that is true religion which giveth to God the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, that due worſhip and honour which hee preſcribeth and requireth in his owne ſacred Oracles. <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>is properly underſtood to be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God which they call</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and againe Godlineſſe is the true ſervice of God, not of ſo many falſe Gods as Devills.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in his booke of 83. queſtions, Chapter 31. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is that which bringeth ſervice and ceremony to an higher nature, which wee call divine.</hi> Which hee ſeemeth to borrow of <hi>Tully, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de invent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Bernard</hi> his Scholler and a ſweete ſinger of Iſraell ſingeth the ſame tune, <hi>What is Godlineſſe but the ſervice of God? Now who ſerveth God, but he that is voluntarily ſubject unto him, and as the eyes of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are upon the hands of their Maiſters ſo the eyes of his heart are upon the Lord his God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Aquinas</hi> the Schooleman being like that Scribe in the Goſpell, not farre from the Kingdome of God defineth religion to be <hi>one vertue, a ſpeciall one, the nobleſt of all morall vertues, which according to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per acts onely reſpecteth God, although according to the acts of other vertues commanded by it, it alſo compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth our neighbour.</hi> And devotion to be, <hi>a prompt and ready will to execute thoſe things that belong to Gods ſervice,</hi> much better then Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who would faine appropriate the name and nature to the orders of their ſpeciall religions, <hi>Religion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is a ſtate of men that aime at Chriſtian perfection by the vowes of poverty, continency, and obedience</hi> as though there were none religious but their Regulars, whoſe religion is in vaine and who <hi>worſhip God in vaine, teaching for doctrines the commandements of men.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152101:19"/>Matth.</hi> 15.9. Now this name religious,<note place="margin">Religit nos religio vni omnipotenti deo; de vera relig. cap. 55. Ipſa religio areligando &amp; in faſcem vinciendo nomen accepit. Quia religioſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractat &amp; tanquam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legitea quae ad divinum cultum pertinent. a religendo. Deum eligentes vel po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius religentes, amiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus enim negligentes, hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c ergo religentes; vnde &amp; religio dicta prohibetur ad cum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectione tendimus, ut perveniendo quieſcamus</note> they deduce and draw either <hi>a religando</hi> from binding, as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let Religion binde us to Almighty God onely,</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> in <hi>Am.</hi> 9. ſaith, <hi>Religion hath taken its name from binding and tying into a bundell, or elſe</hi> a relegendo, <hi>becauſe a religious man handleth and recounteth thoſe things which belong to Gods worſhip.</hi> Or elſe as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine. Lib.</hi> 10. <hi>de civit. Dei cap.</hi> 4. a relegendo. <hi>Chooſing God, or rather chooſing him anew, for wee had loſt him negligently, therefore chooſing him anew from whence religion is ſaid to be derived, wee goe to him by love, that when we come to him we may reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it is the manner of the Holy Ghoſt to inſiſt upon the ſame thing, to ſpeake it againe in other termes, no doubt both for the farther expreſſion of it to us, and alſo impreſſion of it in us, as; <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe tranſgreſſion is forgiven and whoſe ſinne is covered, Pſal.</hi> 32.1 ſo here <hi>Cornelius</hi> is not onely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a devout or religious man, but the ſame thing is amplified and uttered in other words importing the ſame ſenſe, and one <hi>that feared God:</hi> For by a fearer of God, the part being figuratively put for the whole we muſt underſtand a religious <hi>worſhipper of God,</hi> as <hi>Ionas</hi> ſaith of himſelfe to the mariners, <hi>I feare the Lord God of heaven, Ionah</hi> 1.9. that is,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> I worſhip and ſerue him as <hi>Lydia</hi> is called a woman <hi>which worſhipped God, Act.</hi> 16.14. ſo <hi>Hierom</hi> expoundeth it,<note place="margin">In hoc locotimor pro cultu poteſt intelligi. <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1. <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In this place feare may be underſtood for ſervice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that which God ſaith, <hi>thou ſhalt feare the Lord thy God and ſerve him, Deut.</hi> 6.13. Our Saviour citing it interpreteth it to be worſhip, <hi>thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerve, Matth.</hi> 4.10. As alſo alleaging that of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 29.13. their feare towards me is taught by the precepts of men, hee ſaith, <hi>in vaine doe they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the Commandements of men, Matth.</hi> 15.9. putting feare and worſhip for all one; in which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152101:20"/>ſenſe the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>Come yee children hearken to mee I will teach you the feare of the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 34.11. that is, the worſhippe and ſervice of the Lord.<note place="margin">Connexa ſunt timor at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> religio, nec mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poteſt alterum ab<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ero. <hi>Beru. ſerm. de donis ſp. ſ. cap.</hi> 4. Timordomini eſt prima gratiarum, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis exord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</note> 
                  <hi>Feare and religion are knitte together neither can the one remaine without the other, and the feare of the Lord is the firſt of all graces, and the beginning of Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now before I come to the inſtructions hence to be learned, I muſt cleare the doubts that heere are raiſed. Firſt how <hi>Cornelius</hi> is heere commended for his feare, ſince elſe-where feare is condemned pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the ſpirit of bondage, and not ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with that perfect love which is in the Sonnes of God towards him? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Ye have not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the spirit of bondage againe to feare, but yee have received the ſpirit of adoption, whereby wee cry, Abba, father: and againe</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.18. <hi>there is no feare in love, but perfect love caſteth out feare, becauſe feare hath torment: hee that feareth is not made perfect in love.</hi> The Maſter of the ſentences <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 34. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. &amp; the Schoolemen his Diſciples make, ſome of them 4. ſome of them 5 ſorts of feares a naturall, an humane, a ſervile, a filiall, and an initiall feare: I feare to looſe time in following of them, and will content my ſelfe to goe the beaten way of that diſtinction of feare, into a ſervile and a ſonne-like. The ſervile feareth Gods puniſhments, the ſonne-like his anger and diſpleaſure, that, becauſe it hath ſinned againſt him and deſerved the whippe, this, that it may not ſinne againſt him and looſe his love; that dreadeth his tribunall as an angry judge,<note place="margin">Alind eſt timere quia peccaveris, aliud nè pecces <hi>Ambr. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 48.</note> this reverenceth him as a loving father. <hi>It is one thing to feare becauſe thou haſt ſinned, another thing to feare that thou maiſt not ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſervile as it is in the reprobates and Divells breedeth and begetteth in them deſperation of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> expectation of hell and torture: but as it may be in thoſe that are ordained to ſalvation, it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152101:20"/>worketh to their ſalvation by being an externall meanes of their repentance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Magiſtrum ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarumlib.</hi> 3. <hi>Diſtinct</hi> 34. <hi>f. &amp; Beru. ſerm.</hi> 4. <hi>de mode benè viuendj.</hi> Et timebat. cum dilecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, &amp; diligebat cum timore. Qui Deum benè timet &amp; amat, qui amat &amp; timer, res illae funt in caelel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i devotione ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatae. Servilitimore timetur ne judicetur in tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſupplicii, altero ne amittatur gratia bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficii. Timor non eſt in charitate quia perfecta charitas foris mittit timorem, ſed illum ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilem, quo cum ſe quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ab opere malo abſtinet, poenâ terretut, non iuſtitiâ delectatur; hunc charitas foris mittit, quam non delectat ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas, etiamſi propona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur impunitas. Non illum quo timet anima ne amitta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ipſam gratiam quâ in illâ factum eſt, ut eam non peccare delectet, quo timet ne deus cam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerat etiamſi nullis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum cruciatibus puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at. Hic timor caſtus eſt, non eum ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as ecijit ſed aſciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it, de illo quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſcriptum eſt, timor do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini caſtus eſt, perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens in ſeculam ſeculi. <hi>Aug. epiſt</hi> 20. Timet illa ne vir infeſtus adveniat, iſta ne often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus abſced at, ibidem.</note> faith and charity as the briſtle leadeth the thread into that which is ſowed, it is the compariſon of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>Bernard.</hi> And this ſervile feare proceeding from the ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage cannot take poſſeſſion in that ſoule that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſpirit of adoption, perfect love caſteth it out, as the thread entring driveth out the briſtle that lead it, the other the ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke feare agreeth with the ſpirit of adoption, and they dwell together like bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in one as <hi>Anſelms,</hi> ſaid of old <hi>Simeon Luke</hi> 2. <hi>Hee both feared with love, and loved with feare; and as Caſsian in Pſal.</hi> 32. <hi>He that feareth God well, loveth him alſo, hee that loveth him feareth him alſo, thoſe things are joyned together in the heavenly devotion:</hi> Thus the Fathers diſtinguiſh, and reconcile theſe doubts. <hi>A man feareth with a ſervile feare, leaſt he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould be judged to the torments of puniſhment, with the other, leaſt the grace of Gods benefits ſhould be loſt, feare is not in charity, becauſe perfect charity caſteth out feare, but that ſervile is when a man abſtaineth himſelfe from an evill worke, hee is terrified with puniſhment, not delighted with righteouſneſſe. This charity caſteth forth, which delighteth in none iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, although an impunity were ſet before it. Not that whereby the ſoule feareth, leaſt it ſhould looſe that grace which hath wrought in it, that it ſhould not delight in ſinning, whereby it feareth leaſt God ſhould forſake it, although he ſhould puniſh it with no tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſorrow. This is a chaſt feare, charity caſteth not this out, but joyneth it to it ſelfe, of it alſo is it written, the feare of the Lord is chaſt, and remaineth for ever and ever</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin;</hi> And hee illuſtrateth it by this compariſon there, an adulterous and chaſt wife, both feare their husbands but with this difference. <hi>Shee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth leaſt her husband ſhould returne angry, the other leaſt hee ſhould depart away diſpleaſed; ſhe will ſay,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152101:21"/>I feare mine husband leaſt hee ſhould condemne me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Illa dicer, timeovirum. ne damnet, iſta dicet, timeo virum ne deſerat; pone haec in animo, &amp; invenies timorem quem foris mittit charitas, &amp; alium caſtum timorem permanen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſeculi. <hi>Aug. in Epiſt: Ioh. tract. &amp; in Evang. Ioh tract.</hi> 43. Eſt timor ſervilis &amp; eſt timor ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, eſt timor ne patiaris poenam, &amp; alius timor ne amittas juſtitiam. Timor ille nepatiaris paenam ſervilis eſt. Quid magnum eſt timerepaenam? Hoc &amp; nequiſſimus ſervus hoc &amp; crudeliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimuslatro. Non eſt magnum timere paenam ſed magnum eſt amare juſtitiam; qui ergo amat juſtitiam nihil times. Timet planè non ne incidat in paenam ſed ne amitta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> juſtitiam. Ipſe eſt timor domini caſtus, ipſe permanet in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ſeculi non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um tollit charitas, nec foris mittit, ſed magis complectitur, &amp; comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tenet, ſimul &amp; poſſidet.</note> 
                  <hi>the other will ſay, I feare mine husband leaſt he ſhould forſake me. Conſider theſe things in thy minde, and thou ſhalt finde a feare which charity caſteth out and another chaſt feare abiding for ever and ever.</hi> And in his 43. tract, upon <hi>Iohn, There is a ſervile feare, and a chaſt feare, there is a feare leaſt thou ſhouldeſt ſuffer puniſhment, and another feare leaſt thou ſhouldeſt looſe righteouſneſſe. That feare leaſt thou ſhouldeſt ſuffer puniſhment is ſervile; And what great matter is it to feare puniſhment? This doth the lewdeſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and the cruelleſt thiefe. It is no great thing to feare puniſhment, but it is a great thing to love righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Hee therefore that loveth righteouſneſſe, feareth nothing. Hee feareth plainely, not leaſt hee ſhould fall into puniſhment, but leaſt hee ſhould looſe righteouſneſſe. It is the chaſt feare of the Lord, it remaineth for ever and ever, charity taketh not away, nor caſteth it out, but rather imbraceth it, and keepeth for a companion, and poſſeſſeth it together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>that the chaſt holy feare which feareth not God for the paines or torments of hell, but with reverence and love abideth for ever; but that which feareth him for the paines of hell is ſervile, and perfect charity caſteth out it. Senſ. de mode benè vivendj ſerm.</hi> 4 <hi>&amp; ſerm.</hi> 19. <hi>Gilleberti ſuper Cant.</hi> Secondly, in that the religion and workes of <hi>Correlius</hi> are here well reported of before <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> was preached unto him, the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> would hence collect, that men knowing God the Creator, and not beleeving in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> may, before juſtification and faith, doe workes pleaſing to God, and acceptable prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to the grace of juſtification, and which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Gods grace deſerve of Gods hands congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity towards juſtification, <hi>Rhemiſts on the place:</hi> but they gather that which the holy Ghoſt never ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red heere. For <hi>Cornelius</hi> was not without faith, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152101:21"/>how could hee pleaſe God whom without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. Hee knew not that the <hi>Meſsias</hi> was already come and had fulfilled all things that were written of him; but hee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as a true Proſelite in the <hi>Meſsias</hi> to come, and like old <hi>Simeen, he waited for the conſolation of Iſrael Luk.</hi> 2. That hee was of the Iewiſh religion both his conformity with them in prayers verſe 30. and their good opinion of him verſe 22. demonſtrateth.<note place="margin">Cornelius cuius el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſynae ante baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Angelo teſtante laudantur, non operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad fidem ſed fide venit adopera; Si enim ante baptiſmum deo non credebat, quomodò oraret aut quomodò hunc deus exaudiret? <hi>Greg</hi> Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idem venit ad opera in fideverò ſolidatur peropera. Nec tamen ſine aliqua fide donabat &amp; orabat. Nam quomodò inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabat in quem non crediderat? <hi>Aug. de praedeſt, ſanct. cap.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius whoſe almes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) <hi>before his baptiſme are commended by the teſtimonie of the Angell, came not by his workes unto faith, but by faith came to works; For if before his baptiſme hee did not beleeve in God, how did hee pray, or how did God heare him, by faith then hee came to workes, but by workes hee was eſtabliſhed in the faith.</hi> And <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>that be did not give almes and pray without ſome faith. For how did he call upon him, in whom hee had not believed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee ſee heere then in what ſenſe and ſort <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> is a devout man, and a fearer of God. Now our learning lying in all that is written, wee muſt learne hence to bee followers of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and walke as we have him for an enſample, what wee heare and ſee in him wee muſt doe, be religious and devout worſhippers of God, ſerving him in feare <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. Sanctifying the Lord of hoſtes, and making him our dread and feare, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.13. For what elſe doth the Lord require of all his Iſraell but to feare the Lord his God to walke in all his wayes, and to love him and ſerve him with all his heart and with all his ſoule, and cleave to him? <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12.20. and <hi>cap.</hi> 6.13. to feare and ſerve him in ſincerity and truth <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.14. And being the Lord yea the Lord of Lords, of neceſſitie feare is due to him, as hee reaſoneth himſelfe, a ſonne honoureth his Father and a ſervant his Maſter: if then I be a father where is mine honour? if I be a Maſter where is my feare? <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. Feare the Lord all yee his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152101:22"/>Saints, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9. And this is not an old Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement belonging onely to them that were under the old Covenant, but renewed alſo to us that are under the Covenant of grace, paſſe the time of your Sojourning here in feare 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. Nay it is not onely the voyce of God by his Apoſtle but by an Angell ſpeaking with a lowd voyce feare God and give glory to him, and worſhip him that made heaven and earth, and the ſea, and the fountaines of waters, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.7. Yea by many Angels, who will not feare thee O Lord and glorifie thy name? for thou onely art holy: for all nations ſhall come and worſhip before thee, for thy judgments are made manifeſt <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.4. Religion and the feare of God hath ever bin the faireſt flowre in the Garland of all the worthies in Scripture, that have gone before us, and remembred either before or without all their worldly riches, honours triumphes and trophies.</p>
               <p>When God had tryed <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull to the uttermoſt and would give him the higheſt commendation, it is in theſe termes, I know that thou feareſt mee <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> would make himſelfe knowne to his brethren for one that feared God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.18. and ſo was of their ſpirituall kindred, before he revealed himſelfe to be their brother after the fleſh. And the greateſt title that God giveth to <hi>Moſes</hi> after all the great things he had done by him is this, <hi>Moſes</hi> my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1.2. It is the firſt thing in deſcription and commendation of <hi>Iob,</hi> that he was a perfect and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, and one that feared God <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.1. and of old <hi>Simeon,</hi> who had the honour to ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> both carnally and ſpiritually, that he was a juſt and devout man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.25. And this duty of religion piety, his ſervice, worſhip and feare, God is not content to preſcribe by precept, propoſe by patterne, but he doth alſo preſſe it to us by the profit of it, by the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152101:22"/>bleſſings earthly and heavenly, ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, of this life and the life to come that ſhall be heaped on them that feare him, walke in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and leade a godly life: I need not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them, as they are ſcattered vp and downe in Scripture the Apoſtle hath conjoyned and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended them together, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. having bid <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> exerciſe himſelfe to Godlineſſe &amp; piety he addeth that it is profitable to all things, having promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come: ſo happy ſhall they be ſo well ſhall it be with them that feare God and walke in his wayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.28.1.2.</p>
               <p>But becauſe wee are ſo forward to flatter, nay to deceive our ſelves with ſhewes of piety, when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the power thereof, with falſe imaginations of the feare of God, when wee doe not make him our dread and our terrour; I will give you ſome of the principall markes of true piety and the feare of God, wherby we may learne whether we doe but liſpe out the <hi>Sibboleth</hi> of Godlineſſe from the lips and mouth, or elſe doe indeed ſound out the true <hi>Shibboleth</hi> of piety, fearing and ſerving of God from the heart and inward affections, <hi>Iud.</hi> 12.6. I will I ſay give you ſome principall markes, for it is long if not impoſſible to deſcribe and diſcerne all, as it would be in directing a travailer to acquaint him with every petty marke in his way, and not to be content with relating the moſt eminent to him: Now the markes for diſcerning true piety and the feare of God in us, are either general or ſpecial. There is a total or general ſhunning the wayes of wickedneſſe, and running the wayes of Gods Commandements. The wiſe man exhorting to feare God, doth preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adde as a meanes or marke thereof, and depart from evill, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.7. yea hee ſaith more plainely, that the feare of God is to hate evill, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.13. And when <hi>Iob</hi> is commended for the feare of God, this is preſently
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152101:23"/>added as a true ſigne thereof that he eſchwed evill, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.1. when the Preacher would tell us what is the concluſion of the whole matter, and the whole duty of man, hee ſaith, it is to feare God and keepe his Commandements, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.13. making that an undoubted evidence of Gods feare, as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wiſhing, there were an heart in the Iſraelites alwayes to feare him, expreſſeth what it is to feare him in the words following, and keepe his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.29. <hi>Hee that feareth God neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecteth nothing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Qui timet Deum nil negligit, timere deum eſt nulla quae facienda ſunt bona praeterire. <hi>Greg. in Mor.</hi> Solus eſt Dei timor qui mentes corrigit, fugat crimina, innocentiam ſervat &amp; omnis boni tribuit facultatem. <hi>Chryſ. in homil. de Ioh. Bapt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to feare God is to omitte no good things that are to be done,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory. And Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> againe. <hi>It is onely the feare of God that correcteth mens mindes, chaſeth away crimes preſerveth innocency and giveth an ability to doe all good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the contrary when wee will wallow in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, drinke up iniquity like water, lye in ſinne and love it, love it and leave it not, when they conſent unto the theeues, and are partakers with the adulterers when they give their mouthes to evill and frame deceit with their tongue, when they ſpeake againſt their brother, and ſlander their owne mothers ſonne, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.20. Nay when they ſet their tongues at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to blaſpheme Gods great and fearefull name, when they ſuffer their hearts to be overcome with ſurfeting and drunkenneſſe, when their hands are full of iniquity, and their feete ſwift to ſhed bloud, when they can defraud and oppreſſe one another in bargaining, ſelling, and buying, when nothing ſtandeth in their way that maketh for their pleaſure, profit, advancement, revenge or the like, or yet when they will not goe to a thorough reformation of themſelves, but flatter and favour themſelves in ſome darling ſinne like <hi>Naaman</hi> that would ſerve God and yet be borne withall in going to the Idols temple, and bowing there to pleaſe his earthly maſter, &amp; like <hi>Herod</hi> who would heare <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> willingly,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152101:23"/>doe many things readily and yet keepe his Minions too, <hi>Marke</hi> 6. there is no ſound ſeruice or ſincere feare of God in them, though they make a ſhew of Godlineſſe in ſtanding before God in his houſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taking his word in their mouthes and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſtatutes, or hearing his word and will, and ſhewing much love with their mouthes, making many prayers unto him, partaking of his ſpirituall meate and ſpirituall drinke, and performing all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obſequies and ſervices unto him; his Saints that truely feare him, doe ſincerely hate all falſe wayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. And as <hi>Abraham</hi> reaſoned of the men of <hi>Gerar</hi> the feare of God is not in this place therefore they will ſlay me for my wives ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.11. So on the other ſide wee may reaſon againe,<note place="margin">è Converſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> men profeſſing to know and worſhip God, give themſelves the raines of libertie to take their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, runne into all exceſſe of ryot, and ruſh into ſinne like the bard horſe into the battell, ſome in one kinde, ſome in another, therefore the feare of God is not truly in their hearts.</p>
               <p>But I come to the ſpeciall markes of piety and the feare of God, they lye either in duties immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately reſpecting God, or men in God. The duties which immediately reſpect God as markes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of piety and feare of him, are either a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of God and his word, or a renouncing of our ſelves in the things of this life for Gods ſake, and cauſe upon the ſight of that great worke which God did upon the Egyptians in the red Sea, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>the people feared God, and beleeved the Lord &amp; his ſervant Moſes, Exod.</hi> 14.31. conjoyning theſe together and making their beleeving of God an undoubted ſigne of their fearing of God; as on the contrary, when men deny the words of the Lord, give no credence unto them, ſay it is not hee, his Prophets ſhall become winde, his word is not in them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.12.15. and that the Lord hath not ſent
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152101:24"/>them but they ſpeake of their owne hearts, there is no feare of God afore their eies, they are as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> calleth old Iſrael <hi>a ſtubborne and rebellious generation, a generation that ſet not their heart aright; and whoſe ſpirit was not ſtedfaſt with God, Pſal.</hi> 78.8. for not beleeving in God amongſt other their ſinnes verſ. 22.</p>
               <p>Againe the renouncing of our ſelves (whereby we muſt manifeſt our piety and feare of God) lieth either in the forgoing of that which is moſt deare unto us in the pleaſures and profits of this life, or the undergoing of that which is moſt grieuous unto fleſh and bloud for his names ſake. <hi>Abrahams</hi> not withholding his ſonne, his onely ſonne from God, is a ſure ſigne of his fearing of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.12. The Diſciples ſent out by our Saviour to preach muſt againe ſhew that they feare God, by their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſuffering whatſoever ſhall bee inflicted upon them, for the working of his worke, by their not fearing of them that can kill the body, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28. ſuch an heroicall ſpirit was in <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 20.24. <hi>I paſſe not for all,</hi> and in <hi>Chryſoſtome againſt all the threatnings of the</hi> Empreſſe <hi>Eudoxia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> If the Empreſſe will baniſh me, let her baniſh mee, <hi>the earth is the Lords and the fulneſſe thereof;</hi> If ſhee will ſaw mee a ſunder, let her, I have <hi>Eſay</hi> for an example, If ſhe will throw me into the ſea, I remember <hi>Ionas;</hi> If ſhee will caſt mee into the fornace, I have the three Children that ſuffered this: If ſhee witl caſt mee into wilde beaſts, I remember <hi>Daniel</hi> caſt into the Lyons denne: If ſhee will ſtone mee, let her ſtone mee, I haue <hi>Steven</hi> the protomartyr: If ſhee will take my head, let her take it, I have <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt:</hi> If ſhee will take my goods, let her take them,<note place="margin">Time Deum qui ſuper homines eſt, &amp; homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes non formidabis, <hi>Aug in Pſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Naked came I out of my mothers wombe and naked ſhall I returne, Epiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad Cyriacum Ep. Feare God who is above men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>and thou ſhalt not feare men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:152101:24"/>
The duties reſpecting men in God, whereby our feare of God muſt be diſcovered and deſcried are in putting on the bowells of mercies and kindnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, in diſtributing to their neceſſities. Though <hi>Ioſeph</hi> at firſt ſhewed a ſterne countenance to his brethren, ſpake roughly unto them and put them in ward, yet in the end, the feare of God even conſtrained him to deale favourably with them, and to let them have foode for the famine of their houſes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.8. <hi>Obadiahs</hi> proviſion for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the Lord, in the dayes of perſecuting <hi>Ieſabel</hi> is a proofe of his fearing the Lord greatly, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.3. Thus have I out of a multitude of the markes of piety and the feare of God, ſelected for you ſome of the choiſeſt, as ſpeciall flowers out of a Garden of all ſorts.</p>
               <p>I have ſhewed you the duty here, that we ſhould all take <hi>Cornelius</hi> for an example of piety and the feare of God, but if mine eies were a fountaine of teares I cannot ſufficiently lament our defect in this kinde. In our evill dayes whereinto wee are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len there is more then juſt cauſe of renewing that old complaint of <hi>David, helpe Lord, for the Godly man ceaſeth, for the faithfull faile from among the children of men Pſal.</hi> 12.1. and of <hi>Micah</hi> Chap. 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>the good man is periſhed out of the earth, and there is none upright amongſt men,</hi> as then, <hi>ſo now there is no feare of God before mens eyes, Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Iobs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of his friends is too true of our times, men forſake the feare of the Almightie, <hi>Iob</hi> 6.14. As <hi>Eliah</hi> a worſhipper of God complained that hee was left alone 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. the multitude was gone after <hi>Baal;</hi> ſo may thoſe that worſhip God in ſpirit and truth and feare him in their hearts complaine, that they are but as the ſhaking of an Olive-tree, two or three berries in the top of the uppermoſt bough; foure or five in the outmoſt fruitfull branches thereof
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152101:25"/>
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 17.6. in reſpect of the multitude that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſerue they know not what, that wonder af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and worſhip the beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. or elſe that are without God in the world receiving and reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing no God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. Wee ſo ſcrue our earthly <hi>Mammon</hi> that wee cannot ſerue our heavenly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, wee ſo obey the fleſh to fulfill the luſts thereof, that we cannot doe the will of our Father, we are ſo ruled by the Prince of the aire, the ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſobedience, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2, 2. that Chriſt cannot rule over us. Wee are ſo a fraid of men, who ſhall die, and the ſonnes of men, who ſhall be made as graſſe, wee ſo feare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually every day, becauſe of the fury of the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour, as if he were readie to deſtroy, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 51, 12, 13. we ſo feare their feare and are afraid, that we doe not ſanctifie the Lord of hoaſts himſelfe and make him our feare and our dread, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.12.13. as <hi>Tertullian</hi> complained of heathen Rome.<note place="margin">Majore formidine &amp; calliditate <hi>Caeſarem</hi> obſeruatis, quam ipſum de <hi>Olympo Iov</hi> em adeò in iſto irrelizion erga deos veſtros deprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimini, quum plus ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris humano domino dicatis citiùs deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> apud vos peromnesdeos quàm per vnum genium Caeſaris pejeratur. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loget. cap. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>With greater feare and cunning ye obſerue</hi> Caeſar, <hi>then</hi> Iupiter <hi>himſelfe out of heaven-even in this ye are found irreligious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards your Gods; when you give more feare to an earthly Lord, and laſtly with you they will ſooner for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare by all the gods then by</hi> Caeſars <hi>Angellonely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the greater number amongſt us depart from evill, doe any good, Gods feare is not the motive, the feare of men, ſhame of the world, danger of lawes, popular applauſe and vaine glory worke upon them; but let them be free from theſe, and they will not feare God, as <hi>Dalilah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon how canſt thou ſay, I love thee, when thine heart is not with me? Iud.</hi> 16.15. So may God to us, how can we ſay we are religious worſhippers of him, ſerue him with feare and reverence, when we are ſlow of heart to beleeve either his promiſes or threatnings, when we ſay that he will doe neither good nor evill, when we will not forſake our leaſt pleaſure or profit
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152101:25"/>for his ſake, undertake the leaſt perſecution a litle evill-ſpeaking againſt us for his cauſe, when we are ready to take our brethren by the throate for the leaſt farthing, and cannot be content to part with a cup of cold water, the leaſt kindnes that is, to a Prophet in the name of a Prophet? Nay wee are ſo farre from the nature of being religious, devout men, ſuch as feare God, that the very name is flouted at, abhorred amongſt us. Miſ-creants are ready to reproach thoſe that feare and ſerue God with thoſe names that ſhould be a crowne of rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. Thoſe are (ſay they in diſgrace of them that ſeeke to ſerue God) holy brethren, zealous fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, men of the ſpirit, devout Diſciples and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours forſooth. But as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid, if mine adverſary would write a booke, I would take it upon may ſhoulder and binde it as a crowne to me, <hi>Iob</hi> 31.35.36. So wee ſay, if Godleſſe men would load us with names of this nature we would weare them as ornaments, not beare them as croſſes. I ſpeake not this to patronize any that ſerue not God in the peace of his Church, I am knowne well enough to be no follower of their follies, but I complaine of the litle religion, and feare of God that is in them that would upbraid either the true or ſeeming wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of God, with the names of their holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as though they would make that their ſhame which is or ſhould be their glorie.</p>
               <p>But I paſſe to the next amplification by the adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aſſociation, <hi>he feared God with all his family.</hi> His religion was not a candle put under a buſhell but on a candleſticke, that it might give light to all that were in his houſe,<note place="margin">Tanquam ſol radiis ſuis illuſtrans minora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidera</note> he was <hi>as the Sunne inlightening with his beames the leſſer Starres. Hic quotquot fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milias negligimus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome. Let us heere beed all of us that neglect our families.</hi> Hee would not have his family like a motley cloath or a medley
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152101:26"/>colour, ſome of one die, ſome of another, ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious others prophane or idolatrous, ſome honeſt and ſober, others ſwaggerers, and unthrifts, ſome civill &amp; peaceable, others cut-throates and rak-hels, but he would have them all in one livery, uniforme and ſutable, not like the image that <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> ſaw, whoſe head was of fine gold, his breaſt and his armes of ſilver, his belly and his thighes of braſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his legs of iron; his feete part of iron and part of clay, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.32.33. He giveth us an example then of that duty which the Maſter of the family oweth to his houſhold, whether children or ſervants, he muſt be that in the body politicke of his own houſe, which the heart is in the naturall body of man; as it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municateth life and vitall ſpirits to the reſt of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ſo muſt the Maſter of the houſhold impart the ſpirituall life of grace to all that are members of his body politicke, and his houſe in the exerciſes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and practiſe of piety muſt be a Church as <hi>Philemons</hi> was, for ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh to him, the Church that is in thy houſe verſe. 2. <hi>Auguſtine in Pſal.</hi> 50. ſpeaketh to his auditory,<note place="margin">Regite domos veſtras regite filios veſtros, regite familias veſtras. Quomodò ad nos per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet in Eccleſia loqui vobis, ſic ad vos per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet in do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mibus veſtris agere, ut bonam ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem redda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s de his qui vobis ſunt ſubditi.</note> 2. <hi>Governe your houſes, governe your ſonnes, governe your families: As it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to us to ſpeake to you in the Church: ſo it belongeth to you to handle the matter ſo in your houſes, that you may give a good account of thoſe that are under you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was not the prayſe of men but the prayſe of God himſelfe concerning <hi>Abraham,</hi> I know that he will command his children and houſhold after him to doe juſtice and judgement, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. And <hi>Iacob</hi> his grand-childe walking in the ſteps of the faith of his father <hi>Abraham</hi> is not content (at his going up to <hi>Bethel</hi> at the Lords Commandement to build an altar there) to worſhip God ſincerely himſelfe, and ſuffer the dregs of idolatry to ſticke upon his family; but hee ſpeaketh to them to put away the ſtrange gods
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152101:26"/>that are among you and be cleane and change your garments. <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> being doubtfull what the body of the people Iſrael would doe maketh a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute profeſſion not onely for himſelfe but alſo for his houſe, that they would ſerue the Lord, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24. 15. <hi>Bathſheba</hi> was neither priviledged by her ſexe, being a woman, nor by her dignitie being a Queene from teaching her ſonne, but wee finde a prophecy of king <hi>Lemuel</hi> which his mother taught him, <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.1. <hi>Lois</hi> the grand-mother, and <hi>Eunice</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther having the faith dwelling in them teach <hi>Timothy</hi> the holy Scriptures from a childe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. The father amongſt the Iſraelites, muſt ſhew his ſonne why he keepeth the ſeruice of the Paſſeover, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.28. Why the feaſt of unleavened bread, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.8. Why he conſecrateth the firſt borne unto the Lord, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13 and generally he muſt rehearſe all the words of Gods law to his children, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7. as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, he eſtabliſhed a teſtimony in <hi>Iaacob,</hi> and appointed a Law in Iſraell which he commanded our fathers that they ſhould make them knowne to their children, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5. And that wee may not thinke this a legall precept aboliſhed in the time of grace, the Apoſtle giveth a generall charge to all Chriſtian parents to bring up their children in the nurture and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4. as no doubt but that thoſe children of the elect Lady walking in the truth were ſeaſoned by her with ſaving knowledge,<note place="margin">Nee ideò laudanda es quia filios hobes, ſed quia piè nutrire at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> educare ſtudes cap. 14. Non eſt paxuiapud deum meriti benè ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ios educare, <hi>Hiero.</hi> ad Salvinam de vidu. Servandâ.</note> 2 <hi>Epiſt. Ioh.</hi> 4. That ſame booke <hi>de bono viduitati,</hi> whether <hi>Auſtine.</hi> or any others, ſaith the widowe to whom it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>thou art not therefore to be prayſed becauſe thou haſt children, but becauſe thou indevoureſt to nurture and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to bring them up godly, and S.</hi> Hierome, <hi>it is no ſmall good deed in the preſence of God to bring vp thy children well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to come home, unto our ſelves, Beloved, we cannot in moſt places be praiſed for ſeaſoning and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152101:27"/>ſanctifying our families with the knowledge of Gods wayes, and obedience to his will. The old people of the Iewes were ſo admirably diligent in teaching their children the Scriptures that <hi>Ioſephus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contra Appionem</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Noſtrorum quilibet de legibus interrogatus faciliùs quàm nomen ſuum recitat vniverſas; quipe mox a primo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſu diſcentes in animo velut inſculptas habemus.</note> 
                  <hi>Every one of our people being asked concerning the Lawes, rehearſeth them more eaſily then his own name, for having learned them aſſoone as we come to underſtanding, we have them as it were ingrauen in our minde:</hi> but amongſt us it is herd to finde a child or a ſervant in a family that hath learned any patterne <hi>of words, in faith and love which are in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. or layd any foundation of the doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh concerning catechiſme-learning. <hi>Iob</hi> was no doubt as carefull to ſanctifie his children aforehand, that they might not ſinne as after their feaſting, leaſt they had ſinned, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.6. But it never troubleth many amongſt us to have ſonnes and ſervants like to <hi>Elies</hi> children wicked men ſuch as know not the Lord. Nay may not the Lord ſend his meſſengers to us as hee ſent the man of God to <hi>Elie</hi> to expoſtulate with him, for honouring his children before God? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.27.29. may not the Lord threaten us, as he did him, to judge our iniquities, becauſe wee ſuffer our children to runne into ſlander and ſtay them not? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13. may not old <hi>Elie</hi> be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in compariſon of us, for when hee heard evill of his ſonnes hee gave them a cold admonition, doe no more ſo my ſonnes, for it is no good report I heare of you, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.24. But having both <hi>the power of a Father</hi> and he <hi>a Iudge</hi> procceded not to correction, whereas we are ſo indulgent, ſo cockring, that we will not diſpleaſe our children at any time, in ſaying, why have you done ſo? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1 6. that though our children be like to <hi>Abſelom,</hi> murtherers, whore-maſters, rebels, yet they muſt be intreated gently, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Emperour father
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152101:27"/>of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great having made tryall of his ſervants which would ſacrifice to Idols which would not, but be conſtant to the Chriſtian faith, baniſhed all the turne coates out of his Court with this Apophthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gme. <hi>How will they keepe their faith inviolate toward the Emperour, who are perfidious to God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quomodò fidem Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratori praeſtabunt qui deo ſunt perfidi? <hi>Euſeb.</hi>
                  </note> But in our entertainning or re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayning of ſervants we reſpect in them pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſonablenes, ſerviceablenes, and ſuch formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of their religion is the leaſt and laſt care, and wee beare with them well enough though they be ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerers, ſwearers, drunkards, curſed ſpeakers at defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with God and all Godlineſſe, Men are combred about the many things of this world to provide them for their families and children, they riſe up early, lye downe late and give themſelves no reſt to ſcrape together abundance of worldly pelfe for them whether by right or wrong, of which Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith well,<note place="margin">Quam curam geris fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum ut cos obruasla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chry mis miſerorum? non eſt hoc filios amare ſed potius necare Nolo tetalem patrem ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant filij tui, nolo ſic provideas, ut magis in. videas homil. 45. Vnum neceſſarium. Parentes qui filiis ditandis omnem curam impendunt, corum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mores negligunt (quantò magis ſalutem dico ego) ſimiles ſuntiis qui magnam calceorum curam habent, &amp; inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim pedem ipſum parui pendunt.</note> 
                  <hi>What care takeſt thou of thy children that thou maiſt overwhelme them with the teares of the oppreſſed. I would not have thy children finde thee ſuch a father. I would not thou ſhould'ſt ſo provide that thou ſhouldeſt hurt them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But with <hi>Martha</hi> they neglect that <hi>one neceſſary thing,</hi> that one pearle of the kingdome of heaven for the buying of which they ſhould ſell all the riches. <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaid excellently; <hi>Parents that beſtow all their care upon inriching their children, and neglect their education</hi> (<hi>how much more their ſalvation</hi> ſay I) <hi>are like unto thoſe that have great care of the ſhooes, and in the meane while little regard the foote.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I conclude all with aword of exhortation, let us then with <hi>David</hi> walke with an upright even foote in the midſt of our houſes, harbouring the good there in, baniſhing the evill there from, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. Let us not entertaine any to ſerue us that will not ſerue God with us, Let us labour ſo to ſanctifie our ſonnes and daughters that they may be the ſonnes and daughters
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152101:28"/>of the Lord Almightie, and that we may rejoyce to ſee them walking in the truth; let us teach them the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the forme of wholeſome doctrine; I meane their Catechiſme, that they may be wiſe unto ſalvation and let our houſes be as Churches and aſſemblies of Saints wherein the word of God may dwell plenteouſly, prayers may be powred out dayly, and holy hymnes ſung to the great and glorious name of the Father, the Sonne, <hi>and the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152101:28"/>
               <head>THE THIRD SECTION</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts 10. verſ. 2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>A devout man, and one that feared God with all his houſe, which gave much almes to the people, and prayed to God alway.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He tree (ſaith our Saviour <hi>Math.</hi> 12.33.) is knowne by his fruite, either to be a good tree by the good fruite growing thereon, or an evill tree by the ill fruit it beareth, and he addeth there verſe 35. <hi>by way of declaration</hi> as it were, that a good man out of the good treaſure of his heart,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> bringeth forth good things: and an evill man out of the evill treaſure, bringeth forth evill things. Thoſe good trees then that are planted in the houſe of the Lord, by the rivers of the waters of his ſanctuary, flouriſh in his Courts, and being forth fruit in due ſeaſon, and with perſeverance unto old age, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1.3. Such a good tree was <hi>Cornelius,</hi> ſhewing himſelfe ſo heere in the fruits of his religion, both in pity towards his brethren, he gave much almes to the people; and in piety towards God, hee prayed God continually. And as God will have mercie and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152101:29"/>not ſacrifice <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.6. preferreth a duty of charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our brethren commanded in the ſecond table, before a duty of outward ſeruice towards himſelfe commanded in the firſt table, when the caſe ſo ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that one of them muſt be omitted for obſerving the other: ſo here in ranking and ordering of thoſe duties, he giveth the priority of place and time to his workes of mercie, although his workes of piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God muſt have the priority of nature and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity acconding to that <hi>methode of prudence</hi> preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by Logicianes,<note place="margin">Methodus prudentiae.</note> when they handle things the later in nature in the former place,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and the former in nature in the later place. Without any repetition then or proſecution of my former diviſion of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parts of this text, in two Sermons upon it already I follow the Method and foote-ſteps of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in manifeſting and proving <hi>Cornelius</hi> religion by the fruits thereof, either in his charity or in his piety: For theſe two clauſes doe both amplifie and prove,<note place="margin">Amplificare &amp; probare</note> both expreſſe and preſſe unto us the former commendation, that he was a religious man and a fearer of God,<note place="margin">Conjunctim.</note> and will handle them both joyntly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as they ſerue to enlarge and enforce the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation given,<note place="margin">Diviſim.</note> or diſtinctly a-part as they ly in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without ſuch reference.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who gave much almes to the people and prayed to God continually.</hi> It was no ſmall thing but enough and enough that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> had already com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him for a religious man and a worſhipper of God. For what the Poet ſaid of Iuſtice, <hi>Iuſtice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth all vertues in it ſelfe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuſtitia in ſeſe virtutes continet omnes. Religio in ſeſe virtutes continet omnes.</note> I may much more ſay of religion, <hi>that it conteineth all vertues in it ſelfe.</hi> But leaſt any ſhould ſay with <hi>Zachary, Luk.</hi> 1.18. whereby ſhall I know this? the holy Ghoſt doth ſhew this by the fruits of his religion and firſt by his charity and compaſſion. Now to make this profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for our inſtruction in righteouſneſſe, I ſay with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152101:29"/>the wiſe man, the thing that hath been is that which ſhall be, and that which is done, is that which ſhall be done, and there is no new thing under the ſunne, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Cornelius</hi> then ſo we now, wee (that muſt be followers of them who through faith and patience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite the promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12) muſt ſhew our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by our deedes of compaſſion, our faith in God by our charity towards men: for as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, who is a wiſeman among you? let him ſhew out of good converſation his workes with meekenes, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.15. So I, who is a religious man amongſt us? Let him ſhew out of a good converſation his workes in diſtributing to the neceſſity of the poore. For as if any man ſeemes religious, and refraineth not his tongue, but deceiveth his owne heart, this mans religion is vaine, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.26. So much more if any man ſeemes religious and openeth not his hand to the poore and needy with him, his religion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is in vaine. Religion lyeth in and is ſhewed by the workes of mercie as hee addeth there, verſe 27. Pure religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, to viſit the fatherleſſe and widowes in their affliction. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in the 112. <hi>Pſalme</hi> having commended the man that feareth God, the upright and godly man (for ſo many termes and titles hee giveth him) by his prerogatives, he deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth him alſo by his properties whereof this is the principall, a good man is gracious and full of compaſſion, verſe 4. his ingemination of his words ſheweth the eſtimation of this note, for both verſe the fift he ſaith, a good man ſheweth favour and lendeth, and alſo againe according to that of the Poet <hi>(I will foretell this one thing to thee, and repeating it againe and againe I will admoniſh thee)</hi> verſe 9. hee hath diſperſed and given to the poore.<note place="margin">Vnum illud tibi nate deâ, prae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> omnibus vnum praedicam, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petens iterúm<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rúm<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> moncho.</note> It is a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion put by Gods people that would faine ſeeme
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152101:30"/>religious, wherewith ſhall I come before the Lord, and bow my ſelfe before the moſt high God? ſhall I come before him with burnt offerings, with Calues of a yeare old? will the Lord be pleaſed with thouſand of Rams, or with ten thouſand of rivers of Oyle? ſhall I give my firſt borne for my tranſgreſſion, the fruite of my body for the ſinne of my ſoule? <hi>Micah.</hi> 6.6.7; by what acts &amp; excerciſes ſhall I ſhew my ſelfe religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us? will plenty of outward ſervices and ſacrifices ſerue the turne heerein? but it is reſolved by the Prophet, ver. 8. that all this wil not do it with ut doing of moral duties, amongſt which to love mercie is a maine one, he hath ſhew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d thee O man, what is g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to doe juſtly, and to love mercie, and to walke humbly with thy God?<note place="margin">More vulgihoc nomen pietatis etiam in operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus miſericor diae, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentatur quod ideò arbitror eveniſſe quia hoc fieri praecipuè deus mandat, ea<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſibi vel pro ſacrificiis, vel prae ſacrificiis placere teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 10, <hi>De civit. deicap.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>after the vulgar faſhion this name of Piety is frequently uſed in the workes of mercy which I thinke therefore commeth to paſſe, becauſe God eſpecially com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth theſe to be done, and witneſſeth that they pleaſe him either in ſtead of ſacrifices, or before all ſacrifices,</hi> Every child of God is truly religious, and every truly religious man is the child of God, theſe are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> follow one out of the other, now that we are the one, the children of God and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other (religious and holy before God) is ſeene and ſhewed by putting on the bowels of compaſſion, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. The Apoſtle ſeeketh out no farther, no better evidence of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and love to Gods name then this, that they had miniſtred to the Saints and ſtill continued therein, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. How ſhall it be knowne that <hi>Tabitha</hi> is a Diſciple,<note place="margin">Termini convertibiles.</note> a Chriſtian (for theſe are <hi>convertible termes,</hi> the Diſciples were called Chriſtians, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.26.) but by her fulneſſe of good workes? and how that ſhe is full of them, but by almes deedes the beſt of workes? <hi>Act.</hi> 9.36. there was at <hi>Ioppa</hi> a certain Diſciple named <hi>Tabitha,</hi> this woman was full of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152101:30"/>good workes, and almeſ deedes which ſhe did.<note place="margin">Nullâ reperinde ac miſericordiâ colitur, (<hi>Nazianz.</hi> orat. de cura pauperum) quoniam nihil aliud tam peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are eſt deo quàm illa; utpotè ante quem mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia &amp; veritas gradiuntur. Beneficentia deo ſimiles facit (<hi>Chryſ. in</hi> 3 <hi>Tit</hi>) haec eſt charitatis mater, proprium Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae virtutis inſigne, per quam diſcipuli Chriſti noſcuntur. Nihil adeò divinum habet homo, quàm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefacere <hi>Nazi.</hi> orat. de cura pauperum. Vbi deus curam miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae invenit, ibi ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem ſuae pietatis agno ſcit. <hi>Leo ſer.</hi> 10. <hi>de</hi> Quadrageſima.</note> 
                  <hi>God is worſhipped by nothing ſo much as by almes,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Nazianzen oratione de cura pauperum</hi>) <hi>becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo peculiar to God as it is, to witte, before whom mercy and truth doe goe. And Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bountifulneſſe maketh men like to God, this is the Mother of Charity, the proper badge of Chriſtian vertue, by which Chriſtes Diſciples are knowne. And Nazianzen, (ubi ſupra) Man hath nothing ſo divine and excellent as to doe deedes of charity. And Leo likewiſe, where God findeth a care of mercy, there he acknowledgeth an image of his own goodneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I paſſe from theſe words as they both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and demonſtrate <hi>Cornelius</hi> religion and ſervice of God, to the handling of them as they lye in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; wherein wee may conſider firſt the perſon <hi>Cornelius,</hi> ſecondly the act, he gave, thirdly the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter giving almes, fourthly the meaſure, much almes, fifthly the perſons receiving, to the people, heere a little and there a little of every one of theſe will take up my whole time now, and put off the laſt clauſe to a fuller handling at another turne.</p>
               <p>The fieſt point is of the perſon giving the almes <hi>Cornelius. Cornelius</hi> was rich in revenewes, high in ranke, being both a Commander of a companie &amp; a Maſter of a family, and is heere a patterne and preſident to every rich man in this world, great man in place, and goodman of an houſe, to goe and doe likewiſe, as our Saviour ſaid to the Lawyer about a worke of mercie, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Timothy</hi> hath a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall charge layd upon him to charge the rich men in this world to doe good, to be rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18. They that have this worlds good muſt not ſhut up their bowels of compaſſion to their needy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but do good unto them, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.17. Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, I ſay unto you make you friends of the Mammon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152101:31"/>of unrighteouſneſſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.9. is eſpecially ſpoken unto rich men: And they eſpecially at <hi>Corinth</hi> that had abundance, muſt out of their abundance ſupply the want of the Saints that were in poverty 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.14. And that worke of mercie to bring the poore that are caſt out to our houſe <hi>Iſay</hi> 58.7. properly belongeth to him that is Maſter and owner of the houſe, <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> being bleſſed of God exceedingly, and become great in ſubſtance, doe ſo abound in the worke of Hoſpitality (a branch of this tree of almes doing) that they tarry not till ſtrangers come to them for intertainement (which yet now adayes is held an high point of Hoſpitality to lye open to all commers) but they ſeeke occaſions to exerciſe it, runne to paſſengers, bow to them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate them to be intertained, profeſſe that they do them a favour in it, and even preſſe upon them till they obtaine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.2.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.2.3. <hi>Iob</hi> the greateſt and richeſt of all the men of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> maketh the fatherleſſe eate of his morſels, and as a father brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them up with him from his youth, guideth the widow from his mothers wombe, covereth the poore with a garment, ſo that his loynes bleſſe him for being warmed with the fleece of his ſheepe, and ſuffereth not the ſtranger to lodge in the ſtreete, but openeth his doore to the travailer, <hi>Iob</hi> 31. So rich was this rich man in every good worke of mercy! Rich men then muſt out of their abundance caſt much into the poore mans treaſurie, for as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Superflua divitum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria ſunt pauperum, res alienae poſſidentur, cumſuperflua poſſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>Aug. in Pſ.</hi> 147.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſuperfluities of rich men are the neceſſaries of poore men. Men poſſeſſe other mens goods when they poſſeſſe ſuperfluous things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto our Saviour, <hi>Lord ſpeakeſt thou this parable unto us or unto all? Luk.</hi> 12.51. So it may be ſaid unto me; doth almes giving belong unto rich men or unto all men? I ſay then, this burthen lyeth upon them principally, but not onely, they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152101:31"/>muſt come with their great gifts, but even the poorer ſort muſt not be wanting in their mites, they muſt as it were beare the heate of the day, but every one in his order muſt beare his part, give almes of ſuch things as you are able, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.41. as our new tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that text hath it, <hi>of ſuch things as you have.</hi> He that hath two coates let him impart to him that hath none, and hee that hath meat let him doe likewiſe, <hi>Luk</hi> 3.11. Hee that laboureth with his hands for his living muſt out of that give to him that needeth, yea he muſt labour to that end, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28. Our bleſſed Saviour though he lived (not of begging as the Papiſts ſay,<note place="margin">Dicit aliquis, pauper ſum ideò eleemoſynam dare non poſſum, ut nullus ſe pauper excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſare poſter, dominus noſter procalice frigidae aquae mercedem ſered<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diturum promiſit. <hi>Aug. Ser.</hi> 137. <hi>detemp.</hi> Impar facultas, ſed nonimpar charitas, Idem in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121. Si potes dare, da, finoni p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lemte fac: Coronat deus intusbonitatem, ubinon invenit facultatem, Nemo dicat, non habeo charitas delacculo non erogatur. Nulli parvus eſt cenſus, cui magnus eſt animus, Nec de rei familiar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s menſura pendet modus pietatis; Majora qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſunt impend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitum, &amp; minoramedio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crium, ed nec d ſcrepat fructus operum ubi non d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt affectus operan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum <hi>Leo ſern deapparit. domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. n decretis diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct.</hi> 86.</note> but) of the voluntarie contribution of certaine devout women which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred unto him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.3. yet he gave almes out of his bagge to the poore, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13, 29. if thou have but a litle, be not afraid to give according to that litle, ſaith <hi>Tobit</hi> to his ſonne chapter 4.8. Some man (ſaith <hi>Auſtine</hi>) <hi>will ſay, I am poore therefore I cannot give almes; That no poore man ſhould excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, our Lord hath promiſed that hee will render are ward for a cup of cold water.</hi> And againe, <hi>Mens ability may be unlike, and yet their charity not unlike; and upon the</hi> 103 <hi>Pſalme, If thou canſt give, give, if thou canſt not, ſhew thy ſelfe affable and courteous, God crowneth the good minde within, where hee findeth not ability without. Let no man ſay, I have not, Charity commeth not out af a bagge.</hi> And ſo <hi>Leo</hi> the great. <hi>No mans revenue is litle whoſe minde is great, neither doth the meaſure of a mans charity depend upon the meaſure of his eſtate. Indeed the expences of rich men are greater, and of meane men leſſer: But there is no difference betweene the fruite of the works, where there is no defect in the affection of the workers.</hi> I end this point with Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that the Commandement of mercie is common to all offices and ages, neither is the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152101:32"/>Publican or Souldier, the husbandman or citizen, the rich, or poore excepted, but all are to be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed that they be readie to give to him that needeth.</p>
               <p>But here may grow a queſtion whether children and ſervants that are under the power of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Maſters, whether wives that are in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their husbands, may give almes? <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> (22. <hi>qu.</hi> 67.) anſwereth, that if they have any proper goods of them but not of their owne either by gift or getting, they may give almes of their fathers, Maſters or husbands goods without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſave in caſe of extreame neceſſity, wherin a man may take another mans goods to give almes with, but otherwiſe <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>if thou haſt, give of thine owne, if thou haſt not, it is better to give to none, then to ſpoile another.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sihabes da de mo, ſi non habes, melius nulli dabis quàm altero ſpoliabis <hi>ſerm.</hi> 19. <hi>de verb. Apo.</hi> Quid confert tibi ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emoſyna, quae de ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia praeſtatur alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us? timendum non eſt, quòd deus non habeat unde pauperes ſuos paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, inſi tu alien diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias. idem de vitâ Chriſtiana cap. 12.</note> And againe hee ſaith, <hi>What doth the almes availe thee, Which is given out of another mans goods? We muſt not feare that God hath not inough to relieve his poore, unleſſe thouſnatch away another mans goods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But concerning the wife, I ſay with our Saviour in another caſe, that if it were ſo with her altogether, it were not good to marrie, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. and that ſhe were in worſe condition then ſervants, who may give of their own, whereas ſhee hath nothing that is properly by law her owne. And did not <hi>Abigal</hi> bring a large almes of her husbands goods to <hi>David?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. which if we will ſay, ſhe did not ſo much freely, as in caſe of neceſſity for feare did not <hi>Ioanne</hi> the wife of <hi>Chuſa, Herods</hi> ſteward, and many other women voluntarily miniſter of their ſubſtance to our Saviour? <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.3. doth not the wiſe man commend the vertuous woman for ſtretching out her hands to the poore and reaching out her hands to the needy? <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.20. And doth not the Apoſtle command women to adorne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with good workes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10. of which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152101:32"/>almes are a <hi>great part.</hi> She then by the marriage band hath ſuch a right of uſe in her husbands goods, though the property be in him,<note place="margin">Magna pars.</note> that ſhee may give almes, doing it with diſcretion, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, ſo that ſhe doe him good and not evill, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.12. and without any pride or arrogancy, as though ſhe would uſurpe authority over him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 10. And now ye rich men of the world, I ſpeake unto you, and not I but the very time alſo, open your hands to the poore and needy that is with you, and out of your abundance ſupply their wants; as God now tryeth their faith and patience by this ſcarſity: ſo hee tryeth your charity;<note place="margin">Cur tu divitiis circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluis ille eget? <hi>Baſil. orat.</hi> 14 <hi>de divit. &amp; paup.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>why doſt thou abound with riches, and hee want?</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Baſill</hi>) Surely that thou mighteſt receive the reward of thy faithfull diſpenſation, and hee alſo after many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts and victories, might have the Crowne of his patience. Let not the paining of your backs with coſtly apparell, the pampering of your bellies in gluttony, and drunkenneſſe, the ſatisfying of your pleaſures in chambering and wantonneſſe, Hunting Hawking, Dicing, Smoaking and the like, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging of your offences in contentions and endleſſe Law-ſuites, the buildings of your <hi>Babels</hi> to keepe your names alive upon earth, the inſatiable cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe to fill your coffers and loade your ſelves with thicke clay, devoure the poores portion, and make you either unwilling or vnable to doe good and diſtribute. Remember, that being Gods ſtewards and not Lords in fee-ſimple of theſe earthly things, your account of your ſtewardſhip will be fearefull,<note place="margin">In pios uſus. In proptios a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> when ſo litle to pious uſes, ſo much to the owne or ill uſes ſhall be brought in. Then, you that in ſtead of making you friends of the earths Mammon, have made you enemies thereof, ſhall in ſtead of being received into the everlaſting habitations, be ſhut out in outward darknes, thou haſt not bin merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152101:33"/>and thou ſhalt not finde mercie, thou haſt not opened thy gates to the poore, and thou ſhalt be ſhut out of the gates of heaven, thou haſt not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thy bread, and thou ſhalt not receive the bread, of life, ſaith <hi>Baſill orat. divit.</hi> Beloved we ſhould be unthankefull, injurious to the memories of thoſe that have done worthily in this kinde, if wee ſhould not acknowledge to the glory of Gods Goſpell and the ſtopping of the mouthes of Papiſts exclaiming againſt our religion for barrenneſſe in this worke, that the publike worke of charity in building of Temples, Colledges, Hoſpitalls, Schooles, Almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, in giving of Lands and ſtocks for the maintainance of religion and preaching, for the good of Cities and corporations, and for all other pious uſes, have beene found more (upon an exact ſurvey printed and publiſhed) ſince the day-ſpring of the Goſpell in this laſt Century hath viſited us, then can be produced for many hundreds of yeares in Popery, when merit-monging was at the higheſt and that we have both better lawes for the proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the poore, and better execution of them then former times had. And it muſt even with an holy boaſting (as <hi>Paul</hi> doth about the <hi>Corinthians</hi> miniſtring to the Saints 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2.) be acknowledged that amongſt us, there are many <hi>Philemons</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh the bowels of Gods Saints, many <hi>Oneſiphoruſſes</hi> that miniſter unto his ſervants, many <hi>Iohaunes Elee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſynaris</hi> who with <hi>Titus</hi> thinke that day loſt wherein they give not an almes, (as <hi>Leontius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth in his life,) many <hi>Dorcaſſes</hi> that are full of almeſ-deedes, give coates to poore widowes and others, in a word a good number reſerved by God that open their hands and their hearts to their needy brother. But yet the greater part of great ones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, lye in the wickedneſſe of unmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, have their hearts hardened, their bowels ſhut
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152101:33"/>up that they cannot compaſſionate the poore, their eyes evill, their tongues full of bitterneſſe, their hands withered like his in the Goſpell, that they cannot reach them out to the poore. Every where wee may finde <hi>Caines,</hi> that thinke themſelves no keepers of their brethren, churliſh <hi>Nabals</hi> that roare out with him, ſhall I take my fleſh whom I have killed for my ſhearers and give it unto men, whom I know not whence they be? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.11. rich gluttons that can let the poore lye and dye at their Gates, Iudaſſes that care not for the poore, no not ſo much as for a ſhew of caring for the poore which was in him. I ſay to them with Saint <hi>Baſill</hi> the fruite which thou ſhalt reape, ſhall be like the ſeede which thou haſt ſowne, thou haſt ſowne bitterneſſe and thou ſhalt reape bitterneſſe. Thou haſt ſowne cruelty, and thou ſhalt reape cruelty, Thou haſt ſhunned mercie, and mercie ſhall ſhunne thee; Thou haſt hated the poore, and he in like manner, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rich was content for our ſakes to becomes poore, ſhall hate thee, <hi>Baſil vbi ſupra.</hi> I have bin ſomewhat long in the perſon giving, I will be ſhorter in the act heere who gave.</p>
               <p>The originall is a doer of much almes,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> he was not a patient but an agent in this buſineſſe, his almes were not extorted by force of mans law, but came voluntarily from him in obedience to Gods Law: were not impoſed upon him by a rate, or taxation, but proceeded from the voluntary deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, of his heart, and it not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th unto us the willing cheerefulneſſe, the ready ſpeedineſſe that muſt be in our almes doing, willing cheerefulneſſe, for thou ſhalt ſurely give, and thine heart ſhall not be grieved when thou giveſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.10. Every man according as hee purpoſeth in his heart, ſo let him give, not grudgingly or of neceſſity, for God loveth a cheerefull giver, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. This is it that maketh
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152101:34"/>our almes accepted, if there be a willing minde, it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that a man hath not, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome tom.</hi> 4. <hi>if we give cheerefully it will be a double almes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In dictum oportet haereſes eſſe, ſi alacriter demus, duplexerit ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emoſyna, &amp;c. Petentem viduam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectare noluit, ut non ſolùm ex munere, ſed ex celeritate muneris bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum operum meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum augeret, <hi>Greg. Mor. li.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>both becauſe wee give, alſo becauſe wee give cheerefully.</hi> Vpon <hi>Iobs</hi> word that hee made not the the widowes eyes to waite <hi>Gregory</hi> ſayth, <hi>Hee would not have the asking widow to waite, that not onely by the gift it ſelfe but alſo by the quickneſſe of the gift be might increaſe the worth of his good workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this cheerefulneſſe diſcovereth it ſelfe both in countenance, according to that <hi>Eccl.</hi> 35.9. In all thy gifts ſhew a cheerefull countenance, <hi>Pro,</hi> 22.9. hee that hath a bountifull eye, ſhall be bleſſed: for hee giveth of his bread to the poore, and alſo in words, according to the wiſe mans counſell, let it not grieve thee to bow downe thine eare to the poore, and giue him a frindly anſwere with meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>Eccle.</hi> 4.8. and 18.15. blemiſh not thy good deedes, neither uſe uncomfortable words when thou giveſt any thing: againe, the readie ſpeedineſſe, for we againe muſt not ſay to our neighbour, go &amp; come &amp; to morrow I will give, when we have it by us, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.28. The Greeke proverb ſaith, <hi>ſpeedy favours are ſweeter,</hi> and Seneca, <hi>It is the property of the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling doer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Proprium eſt libenter facienti cito facere.</note> Nay wee muſt be ſo farre from putting off in theſe workes of mercy, that wee muſt not ſtill carry till wee are ſued to, but muſt prevent our ſuitours, like our heavenly father who preventeth the King with bleſsings of goodneſſe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.3. <hi>This is perfect mercy,</hi> that we prevent the ſuites of the needy,<note place="margin">Haeceſt perfecta miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia, <hi>Aug. homil.</hi> 39. <hi>rom.</hi> 10. Ingratum eſt benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quod diu inter manus dantis haefit <hi>Seneca</hi> de benef.</note> and releeve the hungry before they aske, and that mercie is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and needeth mercy which is extorted by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate prayers; ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin. That is an unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come benefit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Senca</hi>) <hi>that ſtuck long in the hands of the giver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:152101:34"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bis</hi> dat qui citò dat.</note>Away then with this grudging giving which God loveth not, this browe-beating by ſowre lookes, this chiding by <hi>Nabals</hi> language, this turning away our countenances, this upbraiding churliſhly which maketh an almes a fooles gift, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 18.18. which maketh rather a ſatisfaction for our injury, then a worke of mercy as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>hom.</hi> 36. <hi>in Mat.</hi> 10. with this delaying which maketh us neere to denying as <hi>Seneca, hee that delayeth is next to him that denyeth</hi> he that doth doe almes,<note place="margin">qui moratur neganti proximus. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> muſt doe none of theſe.</p>
               <p>But I am briefe as I promiſed and come in the third place to the matter given, almes; it ſignifieth properly mercies or compaſſions,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the cauſe from whence they muſt proceed being put for the effect, mercy for almes, and they are not onely ſo called but by a generall name both <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16. well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> dooing of good, the denomination being made <hi>from the more excellent part,</hi> and alſo righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112. becauſe they are a fruite of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.10. a ſtreame of that fountaine,<note place="margin">A praeſtantiori parts</note> a ſpeciall of that generall, a ſigne of righteouſneſſe according to that of <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.10. <hi>a righteous man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth the life of his beaſt, &amp;c.</hi> and an outward act of releeving thoſe whom wee inwardly commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Iuſtitiam.</note> Hence it is that not onely the vulgar Bible tranſlateth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iuſtitiam righteouſneſſe, Mat.</hi> 6.1. take heede that you do not your righteouſneſſe before men; but alſo the Seventy Interpreters in the old Teſtament where it is <hi>Hida<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hah righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in the Hebrew</hi> turne it,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>deliver the poore his pledge and it ſhall be righteouſneſſe to thee before the Lord, &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.13. And there are called mercies or compaſſion, as alſo in the <hi>Hebrew Chaſed,</hi> pitty, compaſſion, to ſhew and ſignifie that in almes giving wee muſt not onely open our hands but our hearts,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that the outward action muſt flow
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152101:35"/>from out inward affection, our contribution from our compaſſion,<note place="margin">miſericordia eſt animi condolenti affectus cum additamento beneficti.</note> for <hi>Mercy is an affection of a pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart, with an addition of ſome benefit,</hi> hence are thoſe manner of ſpeakings in ſcripture, hee that hath mercy to the poore is happy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.21. hee that hath pity on the poore lendeth unto the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.17. to love mercie, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.7. Hee that ſheweth mercy <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8. If thou draw out thy ſoule to the hungry, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.10. and 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.17. Who ſo hath this worlds good, and ſeeth his brother hath need, &amp; ſhutteth up his bowels of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſsion from him, bowels of mercies, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. Thus as <hi>Iob</hi> was grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in his ſoule for the poore, <hi>Iob.</hi> 30.25. So the Apoſtle requireth that wee ſhould be kindly affectioned one towards another with brotherly love, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8. and weepe with them that weepe verſe, 15. <hi>Hee giveth perfectly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ille perfectè tribule, qui cume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quod afflicto porrigit, afflict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> animunin ſe ſumit, ut prius in ſe dolentis paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sferat, &amp; tune contra dolerem illius per miniſterium concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat plus cumpati quàm dare. Praebere quod eſt extra ſeipſum. Aliquid de ſemetipſo dare. Affectus nomen im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit operi quum miſericordiae cauſâ largiaris.</note> 
                  <hi>who with that which hee reacheth out to the afflicted, taketh alſo upon himſelfe the mind and affection of the afflicted, ſo that firſt hee tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon himſelfe the paſsion of him that is grieved, and then by his miniſtring to him, giveth ſupply againſt his griefe, Greg. moral.</hi> and hee ſaith that it is <hi>more to have compaſſion then to give an almes, becauſe he that is compaſſionate, giveth ſomewhat from within himſelfe but the almes doer giveth from without him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> And Saint <hi>Ambroſe in offic.</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the name of the affection is put upon the worke when thou giveſt for mercy ſake.</hi> That our almes then may bee the almes that God hath required, let our inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection goe with the outward action, let our grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for our brothers miſerie, worke in us a relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of his neceſſity, as our Saviour having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on the people, fed the hungry, gave ſight to the blind, and healed the ſicke: for want of this, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee diſtribute not at all, or not well, cheerfully in heart, countenance, and tongue, and readily in the worke done</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:152101:35"/>
Now to ſtirre us up to this work of works, this action both of mercie and righteouſneſſe too: in ſearching the Scriptures, I finde a cloud of motives, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the time ſtraiteneth me, I will onely inſiſt, on theſe three, the eſtimation of our workes of mercie now, the commemoration of them hereafter, and the remuneration of them forever. For the eſtimation of them it is ſuch, that what wee doe unto our brethren therein, is accounted done unto Chriſt, what wee deny unto them, is reckoned to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyed unto him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.40.45. As when the loweſt and leaſt member of the myſticall body of the Church is touched, Chriſt the head thereof is grieved, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4.5. So when the leaſt worke of mercy, a Cup of cold water is given to a Diſciple in the name of a Diſciple, Chriſt the maſter is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, <hi>hee that hath pitty on the poore lendeth unto the Lord, Prov.</hi> 19.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Manus pauperis eſt gazophylacium Chriſti. &amp; quicquid pauper ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit, Chriſtus acceptat.</note>
                  <hi>The poore mans hand is Chriſts treaſury, and what the poore receiveth, Chriſt himſelfe accepteth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter Chryſologus.</hi> For the commemoration here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, they ſhall be had in remembrance at the laſt day, either before or without any mention of our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther workes; <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world, for I was an hungred and ye gave me meate. I was thirſtie and ye gave me drinke, I was a ſtranger, and yee tooke me in: naked and yee cloathed me: I was ſicke and yee viſited me: I was in priſon and ye come unto mee, Matth.</hi> 25.34.35.36. Our praying, preaching, participating of the Sacraments, Chaſtity, temperance, honouring of Parents, loving of truth, yea Martyrdome it ſelfe, ſhall ſeeme to be omitted and our good deedes in communicating <hi>to the neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Gods Saints,</hi> principally to be remembred, <hi>God concealeth all the other good deedes of righteous
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152101:36"/>men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tacet Donlinus omnia caetera rectè facta juſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; ſolas eleemoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas commemorare dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus eſt, tacuit omnia male facta iniquorum, &amp; ſolam ſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itatem ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emoſynae increpandam eſſe judicat, <hi>Aug. tom.</hi> 10 <hi>homil</hi> 28. In regno caeli coram omnibus Angelis, in conventu reſurgentium quòd <hi>Abel</hi> paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſit, quòd mundum conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uavit <hi>Noe,</hi> quòd <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> fidem ſervavit, quòd <hi>Moyſes</hi> legem tulit quòd <hi>Petrus</hi> crucem <hi>Ieſu</hi> reſupinus aſcendit, deus tacet, &amp; clamat folùm, quòd pauper comedit, dicens eſurivi. Si vis eſle mercator op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus, fae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>crator egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, da quod non pote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nere, ut recipias quod non potes amitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, da modicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ut recipias centuplum da tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem poſſeſſionem, ut conſequaris haeredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem aeternam, <hi>Aug in Ep.</hi> Mercatura tua negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tió<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> caelum eſt, da pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; accipe Paradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, parva da &amp; magna ſuſcipe, da mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia &amp; recipe immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia <hi>Chry. hom.</hi> 9. <hi>de panit</hi> Non tam propter pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peres, quàm propter impendentes eleemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynas d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us inſtituit, <hi>Chryſ hom.</hi> 37. <hi>adpopulum Antiochenum.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and vouchſafeth to reckon up our almes onely; hee concealeth againe all the evill deedes of wicked men, and judgeth that onely barrenneſſe in doing almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes is to be rebuked,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin, and Chryſologus</hi> againe, <hi>In the Kingdome of heaven before all the Angels, in the aſſembly of them that riſe againe, God concealeth that Abel ſuffered, that Noah preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the world, that Abraham kept the faith, that Moſes gave the Law, that Peter went up to the croſſe of Chriſt with his feete upward, and hee onely ſpeaketh of that which the poore eateth, ſaying I was hungry and yee fed me, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for the remuneration of them hereafter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee give nothing but what wee have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, though wee be not owners, but Stewards of theſe earthly goods, yet Chriſt will reward (not in merit but in mercie) our almes in earth with trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in heaven, the beſtowing of our earthly Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, with a receiving of us into the heavenly habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.9. We ſhall be recompenſed at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the juſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.14. <hi>If thou wilt be an excellent Merchant, a notable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer, give that which thou canſt not hold, that thou maiſt receive that which thou canſt not looſe, give a little that thou maiſt receive an hundred-fold, give thy temporall poſſeſſion that thou maiſt obtaine an everlaſting inheritance,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> likewiſe, <hi>thy Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe and trafficke is heaven, give bread and receive paradiſe, give litle things and receive great things, give mortall things and receive immortall things. In doing then ſome good unto the poore, wee doe more unto our ſelves; For</hi> (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith) <hi>God hath ordeined almes not ſo much for the poore, as for the beſtowers ſakes,</hi> as <hi>Lucullus</hi> that <hi>magnificent Romane anſwered ſome Grecians marvelling why hee inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them ſo bountifully, ſomewhat, O Guests, for your
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152101:36"/>ſake, but the greateſt part is for</hi> Lucullus <hi>owne ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Nonnihil, oho ſpites veſtrâ cauſâ, ſed maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma pars <hi>Luculli gratiâ Plut. in Rom. Apop.</hi>
                  </note>Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, the poore may ſay unto thee that I in receiving almes give no leſſe unto thee, then thou in beſtowing them giveſt unto me. For if there were not ſome to receive thine almes, thou couldſt not give earth and receive heaven. Let us then ſo eſteeme this eſtimation, ſo remember this commemoration, ſo have an eye to this recompence of reward, that wee may never be wearie of this wel-doing.</p>
               <p>And ſo I come to the meaſure, hee gave <hi>much almes.</hi> Hee was not like the Lyons denne in the fable that received all things, but let nothing goe but as hee had received plentifully of God, ſo hee did miniſter plentifully to the wants of his poore brethren. The rich men of the world then muſt do that which they ſee in him, be rich in diſtributing according to <hi>Pauls</hi> precept 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and old <hi>Tobias</hi> to his ſonne, if thou haſt abundance, give almes accordingly, Chap. 4.8. To this purpoſe is that commendation of the Godly man, that hee hath diſperſed, ſowed his almes liberally, as the husband man doth his ſeed, and of <hi>Dorcas, Act.</hi> 9. and the Apoſtle would have it a matter of bounty not of covetouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5. oppoſing it to cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe as being contrary to it. And to ſet an edge to us herein, let us remember that our liberality in this kinde is not our loſſe, but our gaine. Hee that ſoweth ſparingly ſhall reape ſparingly, and hee that ſwoeth bountifully ſhall reape bountifully 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. according to that of the <hi>Wiſeman,</hi> there is that ſcatteret hand yet increaſeth <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.24. Vpon the multiplying of the loaves wherewith Chriſt fed the poore, <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>in Ioh, cap.</hi> 18. <hi>Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is commended to us in this Miracle, and it is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152101:37"/>ſaid as it were with a loude voyce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Liberalitas nobis hoc miraculo commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; quaſi magnâ voce dicitur, Quantò plura dabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liberaliter &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricorditer, tantò tibi, plura largiùs confluent. Eleemoſyna non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pauperat ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ditat, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſum enim eſt, date &amp; dabitur vobis, <hi>Chryſ.</hi> Vt dives ſis, tua largiter da, ut colligas diſperge, imitate ſeminantem ſeminain benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus ut de benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus metas. <hi>Homil.</hi> 53. <hi>&amp;</hi> 68. <hi>ad popul. Antioch.</hi> Exhaurire fontem libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitatis, <hi>Cicero.</hi> Ne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitas liberalitate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereat. <hi>Hierom. ad Paul.</hi> Dabo egenti, ſed non ut ipſe egeam, ſuccurro perituto, ſed non ut ipſe perea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eca.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>by how much thou ſhalt give many things liberally &amp; mercifully, by ſo much many things ſhall increaſe more largely to thee.</hi> And <hi>Chryſoſtome, Almes impoveriſheth not but inricheth, for it is promiſed give, and it ſhall be given to you, and againe that thou maiſt be rich, give thine owne freely, that thou maiſt gather, ſcatter, imitate the ſower; ſowe plentifully, that thou mayeſt reape plentifully.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet our liberality muſt be proportioned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our ability, unleſſe in caſe of urgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, wherein wee muſt exceede our abilitie, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3. according to thy abilitie ſtretch out thy hand and give, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 14.13. Give unto the moſt high as hee hath enriched thee, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 35.10. and the Apoſtles rule is, as God hath proſpered every man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. <hi>We muſt take deede that we do not drawe out the fountaine of liberality as Tully</hi> ſaith, <hi>and that our liberality periſh not by liberality,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierom, It is the wiſe Moraliſts rule, I will give to the needy, but not that I ſhould neede my ſelfe, I will helpe him that is ready to periſh, but not that I ſhould periſh my ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the rich churles of our times conſider this who like him that having vowed <hi>Hecatombes</hi> to <hi>Iupiter</hi> for his deliverance, ſerved him at laſt with Date-ſhels, ſo they owing great gifts to Gods trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury come in with their mites and moates. Their proportion for their almes is after S. <hi>Pauls</hi> preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Timothy</hi> for his diet, uſe a litle wine ſaith hee, give a little almes ſay they, Clouds they are that can yeelde but a drop or two, and fly away, not a whole ſhower; their liberality is limited to a Chriſtmas ſeaſon, afterwards their Gates are ſhut like <hi>Ierich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> Gates, as though all other times were out of ſeaſon, but they muſt know that that rule meeteth them, unto whomſoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er much is given, of him ſhall be much required, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152101:37"/>
I muſt intreate your patience for the finiſhing of the laſt clauſe, which is of the perſons receiving his almes, <hi>the people.</hi> It is meant of all ſorts amongſt the people that needed and asked almes, for wee muſt give to them that neede, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28. to every one that asketh, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.30. but not <hi>to him that asketh eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Omni petenti, ſed non omnia petenti, ut <hi>Auguſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de ſerm, domini in mont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> if wee deſire to have them diſtinguiſhed into their kindes, wee ſhall finde ſixe ſortes named by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.35. <hi>The hungry, thirſty ſtranger or harbourleſſe, the naked, ſicke and priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> to theſe wee may adde out of <hi>Eſay.</hi> 58.6.7. The oppreſſed and exiled, eſpecially thoſe which ſuffer thoſe things for the truthes ſake and out of <hi>Nehe.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.12. Thoſe that are indebted above their abilities, the Lame, the blinde, the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the decrepite, the aged, the poore widowes and fatherleſſe: if wee deſire to know what order wee have to keepe in doing theſe workes of mercy, to theſe poore of all ſorts, we have a rule of Saint <hi>Auſtin, Seeing thou canſt not doe good unto all, thou muſt especially provide for thoſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cum omnibus prodeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non poſſis, his potiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm conſulen dum eſt qui pro locorum et temporum, &amp; quarum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet rerum opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus conſtrictiùs tibi quaſi quadam ſorte junguntur, in <hi>Doct. Chriſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 28,</note> 
                  <hi>who according to the conveniences of places and times, and all kindes of matters and affaires are more narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly linked unto thee, as it were by a certaine Lot;</hi> as to open this a little, in doing mercie wee muſt preferre our Wives before all other, our Parents before our Children, our Children and our family before others, our ſpirituall kindred before our kindred in the fleſh, our kindred before common friends and neighbours, theſe before ſtrangers, ſtrangers before enemies, and ſo excepting our parents and thoſe under our owne charge; wee are to preferre thoſe that are linked unto us in many of theſe bands, before others but ſingly tyed to us, as a Godly kinſman, before one religious but not of our kindred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or one of our kindred
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152101:38"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152101:38"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152101:39"/>but religious, a kinſman, neighbour, and friend, before one that is but kinſman, neighbour, or friend, <hi>Gregorie</hi> commeth heere this when hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Inliberalitate modus adhibendus eſt perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum ut primum juſtis deinde peccatoribus, quibus tamen prohibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur dare, non quia ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ſed quia peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in <hi>Ep.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>In liberality regard is to be had of the perſons, that firſt wee ſhould give to righteous men, then to ſinners, to whom yet we are forbidden to give, not becauſe, they are men, but becauſe they are ſinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in caſes of extreame neceſſity, wee muſt breake theſe rankes, and releeve even our enemies ready to periſh, before our kindred and friends though in great want, and ſo thoſe in greater neede before thoſe in leſſe, having an eſpeciall reſpect to thoſe whom God in his providence offereth to us, as the wounded man was to the Samaritan, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.33.</p>
               <p>But what if wee be uncertaine whether any of theſe kinds of poore be wicked or no? Nay what if wee know them certainely wicked and vitious? I ſay if it be doubtfull, let us not be over-curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſearching, if <hi>Abraham</hi> had done ſo, he had miſſed to entertaine Angels ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome in Rom.</hi> 12. be not (ſaith <hi>Nazianzen</hi>) overcurious to examine, who is worthy, Seeing it is better to give to the unworthy for love of the worthy, then to hazard it, that the worthy ſhould be defrauded for a ſuſpition of unworthineſſe. Our Saviour did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out curioſity kiſſe <hi>Iudas</hi> that killed him: if he be certainely wicked, wee muſt be mercifull as our heavenly father is mercifull, who cauſeth the Sunne to ſhine on the evill and on the good, and ſendeth raine on the juſt and on the unjuſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.45. They are called almes becauſe wee give to unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>and we give not to the manners, but to the men,</hi> as <hi>Laertius</hi> reporteth that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> anſwered in ſuch a caſe,<note place="margin">Non moribus damus ſed <hi>hommi Chryſ. conc.</hi> 2. <hi>de lar.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Laertias Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>I gave it not to the man but to humane condition, I pittied not the manners but
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152101:39"/>the man, and Hierom</hi> ſaith <hi>well,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Non homini ſed huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ſorti dedi, non more ſed hominem commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeratus; Qui indigenti eleemoſynam tribuit nec prodelicto ſpernit, miſericord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> am verè ſcivit; natura enim re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicienda non perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Hieron. in Eccl.</hi> 12. Duo nominaſunt, aliud quod homo, aliud quod peccator; Quod homo opuseſt dei, quodpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator opus eſt hominis, da operidei, noli operi hominis.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that giveth an almes to the needy, and deſpiſeth him not for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, ſheweth mercy truly; For the nature is to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, not the perſon.</hi> Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath a pretty diſtinction in this kinde; <hi>There are two names, one that hee is a man, another that bee is a ſinner, that hee is a man is the worke of God, that hee is a ſinner is the worke of man, give to the worke of God, give not to the worke of man.</hi> And he interpreteth what it is to give to the worke of man, to a ſinner in regard of his ſinne, to an Hunter, Stage player or Harlot, in reſpect of their profeſſion, <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 102. But as for thoſe ſturdy, vagrand and lazy droanes who being ſtrong to labour, will eate and not worke, who have taken up Satans trade to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the earth, who live without God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Magiſtrate, without Miniſter, without cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the world, wee muſt withdraw our ſelves from them, if they will not worke they muſt not eate, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6.10. if their extreame neceſſity be ſuch that they muſt have an almes, yet, their impiety deſerveth a rodde for their backes, and it is the beſt almes that can be done to them, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the lawes made againſt them, both that they may be brought into order, and alſo that the truly poore may receive that which theſe drones de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure. Theſe are the perſons that wee muſt doe almes to, and in ſuch ranke and order as I have recited. It is no being mercifull or doing of almes if wee feaſt our rich friends, or neighbours, if we give great gifts to our betters, or equals, either to curry favour, ſhunne diſpleaſure, or becauſe wee have or would recieve a like or greater benefit; if wee keepe an open and diſſolute houſe for drunkards and good fellowes, the one may be civill courteſie, the other uncivill prodigality,<note place="margin">Laudent tejelunantium viſcera, non er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctantium plena convivia, <hi>Hieron.</hi>
                  </note> neither Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity. <hi>Let the bowels of the hungry praiſe thee,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152101:40"/>not the full bankets of the Gorbellies</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ierom</hi> He that conſidereth the poore and needy is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The Lord give us underſtanding as in all things, ſo in this, that ſhewing mercy wee may finde it <hi>with the Lord in that day. Now to God the Father &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:152101:40"/>
               <head>THE FOVRTH SECTION</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts 10. verſ. 2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>A devout man, and one that feared God with all his houſe, which gave much almes to the people, and prayed to God alway.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Come to you now this fourth time with that commendation which the ſpirit of truth (whoſe teſtimonie wee know to be true) giveth of this religious proſelite <hi>Cornelius.</hi> Now hee was not like the mongrell brood of thoſe Iewes, who had marryed wives of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> that ſpake halfe in the language of the Iewes, halfe in the language of <hi>Aſhdod, Neh.</hi> 13.23.24. Hee was not religious by halfes, hee ſerved not God in an unrighteous holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as many who profeſſe to know God and to be zealous for him, yet will do no good amongſt their people, or in an unholy righteouſneſſe, as they who are ready to doe good, and ſhew great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe amongſt their people with whom they dwell, but care not for the matters of religion, and Gods
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152101:41"/>ſervice what it become of them, but with the love of his neighbour whom hee had ſeene hee joyned the love of God whom hee had not ſeene, with charity towards men, hee practiſed petty towards God and prayed God continually. Wherein <hi>all things are</hi> 3 <hi>things</hi> (<hi>as</hi> 3 <hi>things are all</hi>) the action he prayed,<note place="margin">Omnia ſunt tria. Tria ſunt omnia.</note> 2. the object God, 3. the manner alwayes.</p>
               <p>I begin with the action, the originall is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> properly a ſupplicating and ſuing for the averting of evill either come or comming upon him,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for the Apoſtle in foure words ſeemeth to make foure kindes of prayers,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. I exhort that <hi>ſupplications,</hi> which are deprecations of all evills either imminent or incident;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>petitions</hi> for all neceſſary good things either temporall or ſpirituall; <hi>interceſsions</hi> for others, that God would free them from evill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> fill them with good; <hi>thankeſgivings</hi> either for benefits conferred upon, or evills removed from us or others,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>be made for all men, for Kings and all that are in authoritie.</hi> But heere the ſpeciall is put for the generall, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hee ſupplicated to God,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e invocated and prayed with all prayer and ſupplication, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6 18. Whereof if any amongſt us be ſo ignorant (as I feare too many amongſt u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are but children in underſtanding) as to aske mee what is this whereof thou ſpeakeſt: as the Philoſophers at <hi>Athens</hi> did <hi>Paul</hi> of his doctrine, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.19. I ſay it is a religious ſervice, wherein wee aske of God onely for Chriſts ſake all Spirituall and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall gifts, according to his Commandement and promiſe, and alſo give thankes to him for gifts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Some of the Schoolemen goe too farre when they define <hi>prayer to be a petition which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oratio eſt petitio, quae ad deum. dirigitur, vel ad perſonas, vel ad perſonam propter ipſum.</note> 
                  <hi>or to ſome perſons or perſon for him, Biell de canone Miſſae</hi> 61. That ſo the Saints may be brought in to have part in our ſuites, but ſuch
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152101:41"/>honour have none of the Saints;<note place="margin">Oratio eſt mentis deve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio, id eſt coverſio in deum per pium &amp;, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lem affectnum. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh the ſame language of <hi>Canaan, Prayer is a devotion of the minde, that is a turning it to God by a pious and humble affection, and Damaſcene, Prayer is an aſcending up of the minde to God, and an asking of covenient things of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now do we looke on him &amp; do likewiſe? <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.17. be we followers of him, that good which we ſee and heare in this good man let us do; as he prayed with all prayer and ſupplication ſo let every one of us that will be of Gods houſhold powre out our ſoules in prayers unto him; nay what ſpeake I of following <hi>Cornelius</hi> onely? Let us take for an example of lifting up our hearts and our heads in prayer, all the Elders and worthies of God that now inherite the promiſes, who in their generations called on the name of the Lord, and ſought his face from time to time, according to that <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.5. they cryed unto him, and were delivered, they truſted in him, and were not confounded. Yea the cheife ſhepheard of our ſoules, who in the dayes of his fleſh offered up prayers and ſupplications with ſtrong crying and teares, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7. I neede not relate particulars, they are ſo well knowne, I cannot inſiſt upon them, they are ſo many in number; Never was any of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that did not aske good gifts of the father of this houſhold.<note place="margin">Non viviturexemplis ſolùm.</note> But in this point <hi>weerely not on exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples onely,</hi> that which wee doe herein wee may doe upon warrant ſealed unto us. The King of heavens mandate is gone out to this purpoſe. <hi>Seeke yee my face, Pſal.</hi> 27.8. <hi>Call upon mee, Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Seeke the Lord while hee may be found, call upon him while hee is neere. Iſa.</hi> 55.6. <hi>Aske, ſeeke, Knocke, Matth.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Come unto me all that travell &amp; are heavie laden, Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Watch and pray, Mark.</hi> 13.33. <hi>Pray alwayes, Luk.</hi> 21.36. <hi>Pray with all prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit, Eph.</hi> 6.18. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. So writeth, ſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152101:42"/>chargeth <hi>Paul</hi> almoſt in every Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>And to ſtirre up our pure minde heereunto wee have a cloud of motives, I will ſingle out ſome of the principall, and thoſe either in reſpect of our ſelves or in reſpect of God, in reſpect of our ſelves, our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to pray, for ſtand we not ſtill in want of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all or ſpirituall bleſſings? in feare of evill falling upon us, in ſorrow through evills already falne upon us. What have wee before wee have received it, all commeth from Gods hand. Wee are that man in the parable, that having a friend come to him hath nothing to ſet before him, and muſt fly to our heavenly father and friend for ſupply of our wants, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.5. <note place="margin">Oratio non eſt niſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digentium, <hi>Aug. in Pſa.</hi> 36. Proſe ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eneceſſitas cogit <hi>Chryſ in Matt.</hi>
                  </note> Who will not ſupply us without asking, for to that condition hee hath tyed his grants, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Aske and yee ſhall receive &amp;c. prayer cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede but from men in want</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin, and very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity compelleth every one to pray for himſelfe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Thus as <hi>Davids</hi> neceſſity made him flie to the boſome of his heavenly father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18 4.5.6. <hi>The ſorrowes of death compaſſed me round about, and the floods of ungodly men made mee afraid. The ſorrowes of hell compaſſed mee, the ſnares of death prevented, me. In my diſtreſſe I called upon the Lord and cryed unto my God:</hi> ſo he pleadeth his miſery to move God to mercy, <hi>turne thee unto mee and have mercy upon mee, for I am deſolate and afflicted. The trouble, of my heart are enlarged: O bring thou mee out of my diſtreſſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.16.17. The very heathen Poet could bid us <hi>pray, for all men have neede of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if we had nothing but our owne neede to in courage us, we might have but cold comfort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For many with <hi>Lazarus</hi> make ſhew of neede enough to the rich Churles of the world, and cannot ſpeede, many with the diſeaſed man at the poole of <hi>Betheſda</hi> lye in diſtreſſe, and none will put them into the curing poole, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. Therefore as on our ſide there is need, ſo on Gods ſide there is good ſpeed, that
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152101:42"/>wee might have ſtrong conſolation. It is not with ſuitours that come to him, as <hi>Abſolom</hi> traduced his fathers government, that none was deputed of the King to heare them a <hi>Sam</hi> 16. Nor as it was with <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts which cryed from the morning to the evening and had no anſwer, nor any to regard them, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18 he anſwereth not as <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedone</hi> with an, <hi>I am not at leaſure,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Non vacat.</note> 
                  <hi>but when they cry with their voyce unto him hee heareth out of his holy mount, Pſal.</hi> 3. <hi>His eares are open unto their prayers Pſal</hi> 34. his proper ſtile is the God that heareth prayer <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.3. therefore all fleſh ſhall come unto him. Nay hee is ſo forward herein that <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.24. It ſhall come to paſſe, that before they call hee will anſwer and while they are yet ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing hee will heare, and his hearing and ſpeeding goe together, this is the confidence that wee have in him, that if wee aske any thing according to his will hee heareth us; and if we know that he heares us, whatſoever wee aske, wee know that wee have the petitions that wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of him, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.13.14. <hi>Whatſoever wee aske the father in Chriſts name hee will doe it, Iohn.</hi> 14 13. <hi>The righteous cry and the Lord heareth, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them out of all their troubles, Pſal.</hi> 34.17 Looke at the generation of old, and ſee, did ever any truſt in the Lord, and was confounded? or did any ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de in his feare, and was forſaken? or whom d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d hee ever deſpiſe, that called upon him? <hi>Eccles</hi> 2.10. How ſhould this kindle a zeale of prayer in us? how ſhould it ſet an edge upon our devotions that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay? upon this that God had forgiven <hi>David</hi> his ſinnes when hee prayed and confeſſed them, hee inferreth for this cauſe ſhall every one that is godly pray unto the Lord, in time when hee may be found, ſurely in the flouds of great waters, they ſhall not come nigh unto him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.6. <hi>the negligence of the asker is worthily reprehended where there is no doubt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152101:43"/>of the mercy of the giver</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petentis negligentia reprehenditur ubide dantis miſericordia non dubitatur <hi>Chryſ.</hi> Nil potentius homine orante. Oratio juſti eſt quaſi clavis coeli &amp;c. <hi>Aug. ſer.</hi> 135 <hi>detemp.</hi> Quando fidelis &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis &amp; fervens oratio ſuerit, ſine dubio caelum penetrabit, unde certum eſt quòd van 2 redire non poſtir <hi>Bern.</hi> Orario oranti eſt ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, deo ſacrificium daemonibus flagellum, <hi>Aug.</hi> Oratio eſt animae ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae praeſidium, Angelo bono ſolatium, diabolo ſupplicium, gratum deo obſequium, <hi>Aug.</hi> Gravis nobis eſt inimici tentatio, ſed longè gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viorilli noſtra oratio. <hi>Bern. ſerm. de. dedic. Eccl.</hi>
                  </note> As <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> ſtrength lay in his haire, ſo a Chriſtians in prayer and as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>nothing is more powerfull then a man that prayeth. The effectuall fervent prayer of the righteous availeth much, Iam.</hi> 5. And like <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtling in prayer with God (For hee wept and made ſupplication, hee had power over the Angell &amp; prevailed, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.3.4.) will not ſuffer him to depart without a bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. Prayer ſo prevailed for <hi>Sodome</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> ceaſed praying for it, afore the Lord ceaſed granting, it both opened and ſhut the wombe, nay it both opened and ſhut the heaven in <hi>Eliahs</hi> time: it removed the Plagues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> freed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of the fiery Serpents, healed the Leproſie of <hi>Miriam,</hi> vanquiſhed the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> cauſed the ſunne to ſtand <hi>a whole day I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> 10. obtained water for, <hi>Sampſon</hi> in his thirſt, ſtrength in his neede to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on his enemies, <hi>Iud.</hi> 16. Brought thunder and lightening from heaven in <hi>Samuels</hi> time, fire in <hi>Eliahs</hi> time, healed the ſicke, caſt out the Divells, opened the priſones for Gods ſervants to come forth, raiſed the dead, obtained remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.14.15 and eternall life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21. So true is it that the <hi>Prayer of the righteous is as the key of heaven, prayer goeth up, and mercy commeth downe, when our prayer ſhall be faithfull and humble and fervent,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>out of doubt it will pierce the heavens from whence it is certaine that it cannot returne empty.</hi> Hence are thoſe Elogies of the fathers given to prayer, <hi>that it is au aide to him that prayeth, a ſacrifice to God, a ſcourge to the divells, and that it is a ſafegard to an holy ſoule, a comfort to the good Angell, a torment to the Divell, an acceptable ſervice to God, and Bernard</hi> ſaith <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, that the temptation of the adverſary is grievous to us, but our prayer is farre more grievous to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If then wee are the Church of God, ſanctified in Chriſt, and called to be Saints let us call on the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152101:43"/>name of the Lord (for theſe goe together 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2) and offer up theſe Sacrifices of the fruits of the lips prayer and prayſe unto him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. making our requeſts (<hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6.) manifeſt at his mercy ſeate. They are no ſons but baſtards that aske not good gifts of their heavenly father. And here I can never ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough bewaile the impiety of a generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of carnal Chriſtians too generall amongſt us that call not upon God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. that through the pride of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance will not ſeeke after God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.3. God is not in their thoughts, nor in their mouthes at all to bleſſe his name; but he is too frequently in their mouthes to blaſpheme his holy and fearefull name, moſt unholily and with ut feare. It is with them as <hi>Gentilletus in examine Trid. conc.</hi> ſaid of the old Monkes, that their faſts were very fat, their prayers very leane. <note place="margin">Tantum orant, utiis qui hoc de illis audiunt incredibile vicea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur, ita nimis hoc faciunt ut hinc judicenrur inter haeretico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> numer-ndi, <hi>Aug. c.</hi> 57 de haereſ. Maxime ſi ad praxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> accederet perſuaſio</note> The old Heretickes the Euchites prayed ſo much, that they were reckoned heretickes for it, <hi>they pray ſo much that it may ſeeme incredible to theſe which heare this of them, they do it ſo much, that heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they are judged to be reckoned amongſt heretickes</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the common ſort of our Chriſtians are in the other extreme, they doe it ſo litle that they may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted heretickes, <hi>if to their practiſe their perſwaſion ſhould be added,</hi> if they ſhould both omit it and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve they ſinne not in their omiſſion. For entring into their chamber and praying in private either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone or with their family, they are like <hi>Feſtus</hi> they cannot get convenient time, like as it was with them in the parable, their buying of Farmes, trying of Oxen manying of Wives, matters of profit or pleaſure, rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drunkenneſſe, chambering and wantonneſſe, hunting and hawking, dicing and carding, and a world of vanities, ſwallow up all their time, leave them none for prayer. Houres, daies, moneths yeares ages are conſumed either <hi>in doing nothing, or in doing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152101:44"/>nought or that which is to no purpoſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nihil agendo, malè agendo, aliud agendo. Domine miſerere mei Dominus nobiſcum</note> but minutes ſerve their turne for this purpoſe, a <hi>Lord have mercy on us, or, the Lord be with us,</hi> is enough for a day or a weeke with them, their ſhort devotion careth for no longer invocation: Nay, with <hi>Gallio,</hi> they care for none of theſe ſpirituall matters at all, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaid of his Auditorie that they thought reading of the Scriptures did belong only to the Clergie &amp; Monkes, ſo theſe abandon prayer and meditation to Miniſters onely; let Prieſts pray, they muſt play out their time. Forentring into Gods houſe they doe it more for faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then affection, <note place="margin">Magis pro more quàm amore.</note> to ſee, to be ſeene of men, then to ſee God in the beauty of holineſſe. When they goe to the Temple to pray, they do nothing leſſe then pray, yeelding their bodily preſence, but ſcarce a bodily geſture fit for prayer, and ſuffering their hearts to runne after covetouſneſſe, or any other wickedneſſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. little conſidering as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>how great felicity is granted them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quanta conceſſi eſt fae licitas, quanta colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta gloria, fabularicum Deo, cum Chriſto miſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re colloquia, optare quod velis, quod defide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras poſtulare, <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>how great glory is beſtowed on them, to have conference with Chriſt, to wiſh for what thou willeſt, to aske for what thou defireſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes teeth are ſet on edge with the ſowre Grapes of the old Adamites and Peodicians who as <hi>Clemens Alex. ſtromat. lib.</hi> 7. ſaith) held prayet need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe becauſe God knoweth our wants, is of himſelfe a liberall giver, and hath from the beginning determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned what hee will give; But wee pray not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint God with our wants which hee knoweth not before, but to obey his Commandement, to give him the honour due to him in acknowledging him the ſearcher of our hearts, to ſtirre up our faith and to ſeeke the bleſſing which he hath determined by ſuch means as he hath appointed according to that <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6 In every thing by prayer &amp; ſupplication with thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, let your requeſts be made knowne unto God, and <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Yee have not becauſe yee aske not, Luk.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Our heavenly father giveth the holy ſpirit to them
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152101:45"/>of death, and what not? no doubt by it hee would make good the intreating of Chriſt by Thomas Beckets bloud Thou by the bloud of Thomas ſhed for thee make us a ſcend whither he is gone up,</hi> in his new learning then though we begge grace and glory, any thing, every thing of the Saints in direct termes, yet wee meane onely that they ſhould begge it at Chriſts and Gods hands for us. But what is this to make Chriſt onely a Mediator betweene God and the Saints, and the Saints Mediators betweene him and us, whereas 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. There is but one Mediator betweene God and man, the man Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> notably overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this error, <hi>li.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>cont. Epiſt. Parmeniani</hi> making the Biſhop a Mediator betweene God and the people if any man ſay you have mee a mediatour with the Father, and I make interceſſion for your ſinnes, what good and faithfull Chriſtian would indure him? who would not looke at him as the Diſciple of Antichriſt? Hee is the onely and true Mediator that maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for all and none for him; <hi>Paul</hi> maketh himſelfe no Media: our betweene God and the people. For if he were a Mediatour then ſhould all his fellow Apoſtles too, and ſo there would be many mediators, and that point of <hi>Paul</hi> not ſtand good, that there is but one Mediatour, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. and <hi>Cyrill. tom. in</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh. li.</hi> 11. ſaith upon thoſe words aske in my name, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. <hi>He addeth theſe words to ſhew himſelf the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hae everba addit ut ſe mediato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> em oſtendat.</note> &amp; that none commeth to the Father but by the Sonne, by whom we have enterance through the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and that therefore he calleth himſelfe the way the truth and the life, <note place="margin">In quantum filius eſt un à cum patre nobis largitur bona, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum mediator &amp; Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifex et paracletus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras preces ad patrem adducit.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 14. <hi>And for aſmuch as hee is the Sonne, together with the Father he giveth us good things and foraſmuch as hee is our mediatour; high Prieſt, and Comforter, he bringeth our prayers to the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the divinity of antiquity, they thought Chriſt preſented and obtained our ſuites not the Saints The bleſſed Saints and holy Angels are not to be invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152101:46"/>in prayers, for they conceive not our inward thoughts, heare not our outward words, underſtand not our ſtate on earth, are not preſent to them that call upon them, are not to be beleeved in, are not Gods, nor Creators, to whom ſervice muſt be done, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.8 but creatures, but our fellow-ſervants whom we muſt not ſerve 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. Nay who would not have us ſerve them, <note place="margin">Agnoſcant Arriani ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos non a creato po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulare ut aux iliator ſit. Orat. 2. contr. Arrianos Quis oinſanum caput martyres aliquando adoravit? <hi>Hier, cont. Vigil</hi> An eundum mihi fuerit ad Angelos? quâ prece? quibusſacramentis? mediator inter deum &amp; hominem oportebat ut haberet aliquid ſimile deo, aliquid ſi mile ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus, ne in utro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſimilis hominibus, longè eſſet a deo, aut in utro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſimilis deo, longè eſſet ab hominibus, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> etiam mediator non eſſet. <hi>Aug. conf. li.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Reav,</hi> 19.22. Athanaſius <hi>ſaith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Arrians let the Arrians acknowledge that the Saints doe not begge of a created thing to be their helper, and</hi> Hierome, <hi>O fooliſh man who did ever adore the Martyrs.</hi> Auſtin <hi>in his confeſſions ſaith, what muſt I goe unto the Angels, but with what prayer? with what ſacrament? It was meete that a Mediator between God &amp; man, ſhould have ſomthing like to God and ſomething like unto men leaſt being like to men in both, he ſhould be farre from God or like to God, in both he ſhould be far from me, ſo ſhould not be a Mediatour. Olympias</hi> wrot to her ſon <hi>A lexander</hi> the great, that if he tooke upon him to be <hi>Iupiters</hi> ſon it would make <hi>Iuno</hi> angry. I dare ſay if the Saints could heare ſuch unlawfull prayers they would be much diſpleaſed, at the giving of Gods honour to them, and cry out as the Angell, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. See thou doe it not, wee are thy fellow-ſervants and thy brethren worſhip God.</p>
               <p>That ſame renagate turne-coate <hi>Spalato,</hi> in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation written ſince his leaving of <hi>England</hi> ſaith, that whileſt he was Deane of <hi>Winaſore</hi> hee did with great joy heare one of his Canons there in a Sermon before his Majeſtie ſay, that he ſaw no cauſe why every man might not turne him to his Angel-keeper, and ſay <hi>O Angell-keeper pray for me.</hi> But to omit his lyes let it be granted which yet is doubtfull, that every man hath at all times a certaine Angell to keepe him, yet by what commandement, by what example is he to be called up n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may we not here ſay, who hath required this at your hand: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. Is not ous an intruding into thoſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152101:46"/>things which a man hath not not ſeene, a being vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puft up by our fleſhly minde and underſtanding, without any teaching of God in his world? <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18. Would not ſuch an Angell (if he did viſibly appeare and manifeſt himſelfe to him that hee keepeth) ſay with the Angell in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſee you doe it not?</p>
               <p>I have bin long in this point, I ſhall male amends for it with brevitie in the next, which is the manner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Collatis teſtimonis dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> We ſhall the better underſtand what is meant here if we do as the Apoſtle did in diſputing with the Iewes <hi>Act.</hi> 9.22. <hi>Shew it by comparing of teſtimonies.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth this more plainely, in <hi>Epheſ</hi> 6.18. when he biddeth the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to pray alwayes with all prayer and ſupplication, taking all occaſions of prayer watching thereunto with all perſeverance and perſevering therein without fainting, and Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 4 7. Saying watch unto prayer, and the Apoſtles practiſe is as it were a gloſſe upon this, night and day, praying exceedingly that wee might ſee your face 1 <hi>Theſſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 3.10. Without ceaſing I have remembrance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3. According to that of <hi>David</hi> evening and morning and at noone will I pray and cry aloud, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17. three times a day, <hi>Dani.</hi> 6.10. and our Saviours words that we ſhould pray alwayes and not faint, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.1.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Meſſalian</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>etickes grounding upon <hi>Luke</hi> 18.1. and 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17 Gave themſelves to nothing but prayer, contemning preaching, reading, participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Sacraments neglecting working in their calling and doing good in holy duties. Men not worthy of confutation, that could not diſtinguiſh the things that differ, but made Gods commandements contrary which are ſubordinate one to another. I ſay in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours words, theſe things they ought to have done and not to have left the other undone. Againſt their error, the precepts of praying night and day, without ceaſing
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152101:47"/>without intermiſſion, without fainting muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood either of the affection or of the action; <note place="margin">De affectu vel de actu.</note> for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of praying, it muſt be continuall, which if it be, the prayer is continuall. <note place="margin">In ipſa fide, ſpe etchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate continuato defide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ſemper oramus. Defiderio ſemper oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, <hi>Aug.</hi> 122. ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum. Saniſtim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egrave; ſic acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur ut, nulio die inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitrantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rta. tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ocand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Aug. har.</hi> 57.</note> 
                  <hi>In faith it ſelfe</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>) <hi>hope &amp; charity, we alwayes pray with a continued de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, we muſt alwayes pray in heart &amp; deſire, for the Action of prayer, it is moſt ſoundly underſtood that on no day the certaine times of praying be omitted.</hi> We muſt keepe our ſet times both publike and private, and beſides theſe we muſt upon every occaſion have certain men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall or vocall ejaculations or dartings out of our deſires to God according to that of <hi>Auguſtine Ep.</hi> 121. <hi>c.</hi> 10. the brethren in <hi>Egypt</hi> are ſaid to have frequent prayers but thoſe very ſhort and as it were darted out ſpeedily, leſt the fervency lifted up with watchfulneſſe, which is needfull for him that prayeth, ſhould be dulled and vaniſh away with long delay, hereby ſhewing that this fervency as it is not to be dulled if it cannot laſt, ſo it is not to be quickly broken off, if it can laſt. We ſee then what it is to pray alwayes, to have a continued deſire of praying, to omit none of our ſet times either publicke or private, to be ready upon every occaſion to lift up our minde to God, and darre out our prayers, and not to faint in all this, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.1. In a word to pray alwayes is to pray frequently, without intermiſſion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly without fainting.</p>
               <p>We have the Saints our patternes and preſidents heerein, <hi>Davids</hi> &amp; <hi>Daniels</hi> thrice a day, <hi>Davids</hi> ſeven times a day, and his midnights prayſing of God. The Apoſtles giving themſelves to prayer, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. <hi>Pauls</hi> praying night and day, his precepts, pray alwayes, <hi>Ep.</hi> 6 18. Continue in prayer, watch in the ſame, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pray without ceaſing, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17. Continue inſtant in prayer, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Annas</hi> ſerving the Lord with prayer night and day, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. the Apoſtles widow con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in prayers and ſupplications night and day, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.5. The parable of the poore widow im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortuning
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152101:47"/>the unrighteous Iudge <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. The woman of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> inſtance notwithſtanding all checks. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. <hi>Pauls</hi> tripling his prayers for his deliverance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 Our Saviours going a part to pray, ſpending whole nights in prayer, commanding us to watch and pray, alwayes <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.36. are well knowne unto us, <note place="margin">Quod pernoctaverie dominus in orande &amp; quòd prolixius oraverit quid aliud quam nobis praebebatexemplum? in tempore precator opportunus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um patre exauditur aeternus, <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 121. Genua in morem cameli ſenſum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tactus an uerint, aſſidui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate orandi. Cum vita defunctam lavarevelient in genibus cubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> concrecam callorum duritiem ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parviſſe.</note> and ſhould be aſwell imitated. <hi>That our Lord concluded all night in praying, and that he uſed prolixity there in what did he elſe but give an example to us, being in the time (of his fleſh) a ſeaſonable prayer to God, but with his father an everlaſting hearer and granter of our ſuites,</hi> ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine. Euſebius li.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 23. reporteth of <hi>Iacobus Iuſtus,</hi> the brother of the Lord, that <hi>his knees like a Camel, had loſt the ſenſe of touching with aſſiduity of praying &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> in his <hi>Dialogues</hi> reporteth of <hi>Traſilla</hi> a Virgin his Aunt, that <hi>when they went about to waſh her being dead, there appeared a thicke hardneſſe in her knees and elbowes. Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> in his <hi>Epitaph</hi> for his ſiſter <hi>Gorgonia</hi> ſaith, that ſhe was ſo given to prayer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nees ſeemed to cleave &amp; grow to the ground <hi>Hierom</hi> in the life of <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Eremite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Propefinem. Etiam cadaver mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum officioſo geſtu precabatur.</note> 
                  <hi>neere to the end</hi> writeth that he was found by S. <hi>Anthony</hi> dead, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon his knees, holding up his hands, liſting up his eyes, <hi>Even the dead carkeiſe prayed with an officious geſture. Theodeſius</hi> the Emperour being to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Tyrant <hi>Eugenius</hi> continued a whole night in prayer, as <hi>Theodoret lib</hi> 5. <hi>ca.</hi> 24. and <hi>Zozomen pag.</hi> 421 report and as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de civit. c</hi> 26. <hi>he fought more by praying then by ſtriking.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Magis orando quam feriendo pugnantes Sicut nullum eſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum quo homo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on fruatur deipietate aut miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rico; dia, ſic nullum debet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſte momentum, quo eum praeſentem non habeat in memoria <hi>Bern. de interiort domo. cap.</hi> 48.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Oh then bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved let us taking theſe whothies for our examples alwayes abound in this worke of the Lord praying without ceaſing, watching unto prayer being ſervent therein, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntinuing in it without fainting. <hi>As there is no moment</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>wherein man injoyeth not the goodneſſe or mercy of God, ſo there ought to be no moment, wherein hee ſhould not have him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in his memory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:152101:48"/>
There is not a more certaine ſigne of a faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord, as the neglect thereof is a plaine proofe of aprophane chart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Cum videro quempiam <hi>Chryſo. li.</hi> 2. <hi>orand. deum.</hi>
                  </note> When I ſee a man that careth not for prayer nor fervently &amp; vehemently bent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, it is evident to me that he hath no good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his minde: Againe when I ſee a man that can never be glutted with ſerving of God, and reckoning it his greateſt loſſe, if he pray not continually; I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that he doth ſurely meditate on all good duties, &amp; is a temple of God. For if mans garment, his gate, his laughter declare what he is, much more is his praying a ſigne of all righteouſneſſe, vertue and pietie. There is no better weapon to fight againſt our ſpirituall adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries and our inward luſts,<note place="margin">Frequens oratio extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guit impugnationem vitiorum Oratio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinua ſuperat tela dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli, <hi>Bern ſer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 67. de modo benè vivendi</note> 
                  <hi>frequent prayer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>) <hi>quencheth the affaults of vices, continuall prayer overcommeth the weapons of the Divell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And whatſoever we doe whether we eate or drinke, let us doe all in the name of the Lord Ieſus with prayer and giving of thanks to God and the Father by him, Col.</hi> 3.17. Let us prayto the Lord when we lye downe, <hi>to lighten our eyes that we ſleepe not in darkeneſſe, Pſal.</hi> 13. When we riſe up to ſend us good ſpeed this day as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. When we goe out and in to be with us in our journey as <hi>Iacob</hi> did <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. according to that of <hi>Hierome</hi> when <hi>we goe out of our lodging, let prayer arme us, when we returne from the ſtreet let prayer meete us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Egredientes dehoſpitio armetoratio, regtedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus de platea occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat oratio.</note> When we take in hand any buſineſſe, <hi>to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the worke of our hands upon us, Pſal.</hi> 90. when wee ſit downe to eate and drinke, to bleſſe theſe creatures unto us; when we performe any ſervice to him, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it at our hands; when we are partakres of his Table let us pray him to make us worthy receivers to our ſalvation, and give thanks to him for that ſpirituall meate, that he giveth us there to eate, &amp; that ſpirituall drinke that he giveth thereto drinke, for hence was the Lords ſupper called the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> of the giving of thanks uſed in the celebrating of it, &amp; an oblation or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152101:48"/>becauſe as <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſaid 2 <hi>Apolog pro Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianius the Miniſter ſendeth up prayſe &amp; glory to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all.</hi> And <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that the Apoſtles uſed the Lords prayer to the conſecration, <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 63. <hi>Iuſtin Martyr,</hi> that the <hi>Euchariſt was conſecrated by prayer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prece fieri Euchariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, <hi>Apol</hi> 2. Invocatione ſummi num inis li. 1. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 1. Iren. grariarum actione, <hi>li.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 57.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian, by calling upon the high God, and Iraeneus, by giving of thankes,</hi> if we walke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this rule, peace and mercy ſhall be upon us from this time forth and for evermore.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:152101:49"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152101:49"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
